<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Esoptron Astrologikon. Astrological opticks. Wherein are represented the faces of every signe, with the images of each degree in the zodiack: thereby describing, 1. The nature and quality of every person, according to the degree ascending in the east at his nativity. 2. The virtue and signification of every planet through the 12. signes. 3. A most excellent description of the more hidden and abstruse influence of [symbol for Mercury] in his [symbol for conjunction] with all other the planets. 4. A clear explanation of the signification of the horoscope in any signe of the zodiack. / Compiled at Venice, by those famous mathematicians, Johann. Regiomontanus and Johannes Angelus.</title>
            <author>Angelus, Johannes, 1463-1512.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 220 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 103 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1617_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209641</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868506</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868506</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170163</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84433)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170163)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 204:E1617[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Esoptron Astrologikon. Astrological opticks. Wherein are represented the faces of every signe, with the images of each degree in the zodiack: thereby describing, 1. The nature and quality of every person, according to the degree ascending in the east at his nativity. 2. The virtue and signification of every planet through the 12. signes. 3. A most excellent description of the more hidden and abstruse influence of [symbol for Mercury] in his [symbol for conjunction] with all other the planets. 4. A clear explanation of the signification of the horoscope in any signe of the zodiack. / Compiled at Venice, by those famous mathematicians, Johann. Regiomontanus and Johannes Angelus.</title>
                  <author>Angelus, Johannes, 1463-1512.</author>
                  <author>Gadbury, John, 1627-1704.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 184 [i.e. 186], [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Allen, and R. Moon, and are to be sold at their shops, at the Sun-rising, and Seven-starrs in Pauls Church-yard, in the new buildings between the two north-doors.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1655]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first two words of title are in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Year of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>P. 186 misnumbered 184.</note>
                  <note>Errata p. [16]; advertisement [2] p. at end.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 15. 1655".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Astrology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170163:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Aſtrologicall Opticks.</hi> Wherein are repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Faces of every Signe, with the Images of each Degree in the Zodiack: thereby deſcribing,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The nature and quality of every perſon, according to the Degree aſcending in the Eaſt at his nativity.</item>
               <item>2. The virtue and ſignification of every Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net through the 12. Signes.</item>
               <item>3. A moſt excellent Deſcription of the more hidden and abſtruſe influence of ☿ in his ☌ with all other the Planets.</item>
               <item>4. A Clear Explanation of the ſignification of the Horoſcope in any ſigne of the Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diack.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Compiled at <hi>Venice,</hi> by thoſe famous Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicians, <hi>Johann. Regiomontanus</hi> and <hi>Johannes Angelus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Allen,</hi> and <hi>R. Moon,</hi> and are to be ſold at their Shops, at the Sun-riſing, and Seven-Starrs in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, in the new buildings between the two North-doors.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:170163:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:170163:2"/>
            <head>On this Ingenious <hi>Tranſlation.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>WHat? Learned <hi>Angelus</hi> in Engliſh<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Say,</l>
               <l>Why deviat'ſt thou from the Latine way?</l>
               <l>That Gallant Road! much beat by learned men,</l>
               <l>Fathers, and Councells; Speak! why turnd'ſt thou then?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas! Since <hi>Littleton</hi> hath left the place</l>
               <l>To Anchor there, th'ingenious deem't diſgrace.</l>
               <l>Engliſh is <hi>Hebrew</hi> grown; Latine poor <hi>Scotc'h!</hi>
               </l>
               <l>We Pray in Engliſh; and in Latine watch.</l>
               <l>Come then you Sacred Damſells, learn to Dance</l>
               <l>By 'th Albion Muſick! <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Goe ſhake your Eares! Brave Brittain is the place</l>
               <l>Of Princely ſpeech; <hi>Romes</hi> Language is High-baſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But hark my Muſe, muſt we damn <hi>Tully</hi> ſo,</l>
               <l>And Execrate that Language, whence doth flow.</l>
               <l>All proper Engliſh: No, wee'l trim her Brow,</l>
               <l>With Wreathes of Bayes and Lawrell; 'Tis her due.</l>
               <l>'Twas not our Authors Aime to ſtrangle her,</l>
               <l>But by his Engliſh Verſion, to preferr</l>
               <l>Her unto all; and for this end hath he</l>
               <l>Beſtow'd his Pains, that after-times may ſee</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Angelus</hi> (A young Tree, bearing fruit)</l>
               <l>Has got a work-days (well as Sundays) Suit.</l>
               <l>He is ſo verdant in the Engliſh, that</l>
               <l>My Poorer praiſe (Alas!) he needeth now</l>
               <l>What ſhall I ſay? If then <hi>Angelus</hi> be,</l>
               <l>So Excellent in Engliſh; what is he.</l>
               <pb facs="tcp:170163:3"/>
               <l>In High-born Latine? Surely hee's as farr,</l>
               <l>Above the Engliſh, As the morning Starre</l>
               <l>Beneath the Sunne; That ſerves for higher wits!</l>
               <l>And this th' ingenious Tyre beſt befits.</l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>Jo. Gadbury <hi>Philomath.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:170163:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>TAke here the fruits of ſome cold Winter-nights which I have painfully ſuſteyned, being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous that the works of this Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Author, (being ſcarce to be had in the originall) ſhould not dye in obſcurity but be revived to ſee the light again: Though I have been both diſcouraged and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diced in my intents to reduce what of art ſhould come into my hands, into the Engliſh tongue; not only by the ignorant and illiterate; (but their reproach I va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue not; they doing but their dog-like nature, to barke at that which they know not,) but alſo by ſome time-ſerving, ſelfe-ended, ſelfe-ayming, ſelfe-applauding perſons; to them I ſay no more but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reader,</hi> the diſcourſe enſuing was pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned above 200. yeares ago in the Latine tongue at <hi>Venice,</hi> by a learned Author <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hannes Angelus.</hi> It being now almoſt gone out of Print; I have endeavored to revive it, and ſuit it to our Engliſh faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
<pb facs="tcp:170163:4"/>here he firſt repreſents you with an emblem of Aſtrology; or an jmaginary I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the aſcention of every degree of the Zodiack; thereby-ſetting forth a deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the nature and quality of every perſon, ſignified by ſuch an aſcendant; which being well conſidered and weighed with the poſition of the Planets, you may the better ballance your judgment in the deſcribing of any perſon, native querent or queſited, In the next place followes the moſt copious judgments on Nativities that ever yet were in the Engliſh tongue; with the applications of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> to every Planet: And as I have herein endured much cold, and paines, in the writing of it; I hope you will reape much profit, in the ſtudying of it.</p>
            <p>I think it needleſſe to ſay any thing in the praiſe or vindication of Aſtrology; its uſe and lawfulneſſe being already well known: but only this I would be glad, if the Vulgar people were not ſo apt to be frighted at thoſe <hi>Raw-heads</hi> and <hi>Bloody-bones,</hi> where-with Mothers uſe to ſcare their Children from running abroad: nor to thinke old women Witches, and ſuch ſilly people, and that they make Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts
<pb facs="tcp:170163:4"/>and Seale bonds to the Devill, ride up and down in the Aire with him; dance abroad like Cats while their Bodies have laine as dead by their Husbands (as if the Devill could take a ſoul out of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and cauſe it to returne againe! <hi>Vah</hi>) haunt peoples houſes, and render them inhabitable. Indeed theſe tales uſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to terrifie one another with; but they could never learne it, unleſſe they were taught by ſome more Childiſh then themſelves; I wonder that theſe which have any wit in their heads, or at leaſt would ſeeme to have, are not aſhamed of ſuch idle ſtories; but the Devill indeed who is the Father of lies is their tutor, and his doctrine they will follow; though nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they nor any man or woman in the world yet ſaw his <hi>Cloven-foot;</hi> but he keeps his ſchoole in their own <hi>boſomes.</hi> And therefore St. <hi>Paul</hi> teaches them how to make their defence againſt him. That e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver there was any ſuch thing as <hi>Bill</hi> or <hi>Bond</hi> by any one Sealed to him, or any <hi>Contract</hi> or <hi>Covenant</hi> by any witch made with him, is impoſſible to be true. I could never yet learne where his <hi>Scrivner</hi> dwels nor who was witneſſe to any of his Bonds: if no witneſſe, then certainly they are
<pb facs="tcp:170163:5"/>fooles that let him take them in execution upon his Bonds, and will not pleade <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt factum;</hi> and make him prove his bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, <hi>perteſtes</hi> the Scripture ſaies he is a Priſoner reſerved in Chaines of darkneſſe unto the judgment of the laſt day; and if ſo, then how he can come abroad to drive ſuch bargaines, I do not know: but I believe the brokers are his Factors, for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them there are many a ſimple Wizard, drawn-in to ſeale deviliſh Bonds and Contracts indeed; at 30. pounds <hi>per cent;</hi> and is not this the Devills intereſt? I am ſure its no Chriſtians, by their Law. Some will ſay, that many have confeſt themſelves to be Witches: that may be; many ſimple people or perſons overcome with melancholy have imagined them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be Birds, Beaſts, Fiſhes, Froggs, Cats, Dogs, Fire, Water, Rivers, nay any thing, and will not be perſwaded by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to believe otherwiſe; then judge you what theſe will confeſſe: Yet all this while I do not deny, but there are Witches, and too many; wherefore it is Commanded, Thou ſhalt not ſuffer a Witch to live; but what theſe Witches are, thoſe who have two or 300 pounds a yeare to do nothing elſe but talke to you an houre or two's diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe,
<pb facs="tcp:170163:5"/>in a weeke; might beſtow the pains to tell you if they would: if they do not, aſſoone as I have another opportunity, I will: But one of them hath puſled him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and all the wit he hath to puſle Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers; and, very wiſely, for want of other Authors quotes thoſe ſcurilous <hi>Ballads</hi> and <hi>Pamphlets</hi> of <hi>Fryer Bacon</hi> and <hi>Doctor Foſter;</hi> which were idle ſtories impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Fathered on them ſince their deaths; juſt like the ſtory of <hi>James Hinde</hi> the great thiefe; the pranks which they Printed of him, as done by him, are all in an old tale-book, Printed above a hundred yeares agoe which I had when I was a School-boy; nay I have heard ſome perſons impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tell ſome things to have beene done by Mr. <hi>Lilly,</hi> which you may <hi>verbatim</hi> read amongſt other ſtuffe in a ſtory of <hi>George,</hi> a <hi>Greene.</hi> And I verily believe when ever Mr. <hi>Lilly</hi> dies; the Pamphlets of <hi>Doctor Foſter</hi> and <hi>Fryer Bacon</hi> will be new vampt in his name. I cannot tell how he can thinke otherwiſe, having had the experience of ſo many impudent lies imputed to him in his life time. But let every one learne to know himſelfe, and keepe the Devill out of his own boſome
<pb facs="tcp:170163:6"/>and he need not feare him any where elſe.</p>
            <p>Reader here is alſo annexed a Sygil of ♄ to be made when he comes into his <hi>Exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation;</hi> which I have the rather put in, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the elected time is now a coming: you may make an experiment of it, which happens but once in 30. yeares; it was taken out of an Antient Author: hereafter perhaps you ſhall ſee the reſt, in the meane time ſtudy the great book of God, and this; and you ſhall ſee them both agree to your good; which that it may, is the deſire of him who is <hi>Amicus omnibus, inimicus nullis, niſi ſibipſi.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>A ſtudio in Arte Coeleſti.</hi> 
                  <date>15. <hi>Jan.</hi> 1655.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>R. Turner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="authors_note">
            <pb facs="tcp:170163:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>William Lilly</hi> ſtudent in Aſtrology unto the Lovers thereof.</head>
            <p>THis kind of <hi>Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy</hi> now publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Mr. Turner,</hi> had its Original from the <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptians,</hi> and was firſt made known to us in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> by the learned Jew <hi>Even Ezra,</hi> from whom I conceive <hi>Johannes An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelus</hi> had thoſe Notes, which he firſt publiſhed
<pb facs="tcp:170163:7"/>at <hi>Venice 1494.</hi> and twenty yeares after re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed; This learning is properly tearmed <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomaeriarum Doctrina,</hi> or a part of the Doctrine of the Sphears; and may be of great Concernment unto parents who deſire to know thoſe <hi>Magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> or <hi>Profeſſions</hi> which would beſt ſuit with the naturall conſtitution of their Children: For this is very true, that if the <hi>Nativity</hi> be exactly
<pb facs="tcp:170163:7"/>rectified, and the true Degree of the ſigne ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>Horoſcope or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendant,</hi> exactly found out, and then compared with the <hi>Decanate</hi> or <hi>Face</hi> of that ſigne, ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſing; I ſay then, much of the Inclination of the Child will be found out, and unto what <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery</hi> he is moſt propenſe: and ſo the <hi>Parent</hi> may accordingly, <hi>ſuite</hi> his Child with a Trade or Profeſſion, anſwerable
<pb facs="tcp:170163:8"/>unto his proper <hi>Genius</hi> or diſpoſition, by which means the Native is like to prove an abſolute Maſter in that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, he ſhall be put unto. I am ſtraitned of time, elſe I would diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver very manifold Uſes of this booke. The <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor</hi> hath very well tranſlated it, and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the <hi>Aſtrologicall</hi> ſence of every ſentence, judiciouſly, I wiſh both the <hi>Tranſlator, Statio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:170163:8"/>and <hi>Book</hi> it ſelfe; a kind acceptance: the matter very highly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving it. Thine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>William Lilly</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:170163:9"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>Page 2. line 6. dele like. l. 12. dele in, and for righ read right. l. 15. r. Laborious. p. 4. l. 18. after ſtanding a. p. 5. l. 14. for retchleſſe, r. reſtleſſe. p. 8. l. 11. r. of eod, r. and. p. 10.8. r. Covetous. p. 16. l. 22. r. aſcends p. 17. l. 11. r. the. p. 22. l. 16. for Virgo r. Saturn. p. 25. l. 16. r. a role. p. 27. l. 6. r. covetouſly, p. 33. l. 25. r. a Camel p. 45. l. 11. r. after ſhoulder, r. it ſignifies a man without Power. p. 48. l. 14. for Venus r. Mercury. p. 53. l. 1. for Aries r. Saturn, p. 55. l. 27. r. of Piſces. p. 59. l. 7. for Crump r. Cramp; l. 13. for Aries r. Mars, l. 20. for Leo r, Saturn. p. 62. l. 1. for Aries poſited, r. Saturn poſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, p. 62. l. 9. for Aries, r. Saturn. p. 63. l. 9. for Aries r. Saturn. l. 11. for. 6. r. Conjunction. p. 66. l. 18. r. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds. Pt 72. l. 2. dele valitious. l. 11. r. rejoyceth. p. 74. l. 20 r. Herdſman. p. 75. l. 13. r. diaffected. l. ult. for Taurus r. Venus. p. 77. l. 14. r. Iupiter. p. 82. l. 9. for joyned to, r. beholding. l. 12. r. he, be. p. 85. l. 8. r. Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous. p. 87. l. 25, r. Lameneſſes. p. 90. l. ult. for, Saturn r. Mars. p. 95. l. 16. for and poſited r. poſited and. p. 96. l. 19. fo. the Mars read that Mars. p. 103. l. 17. r. laſcivious. p. 114. l. 23. r. fortune. p. 116. l. 22. r. aſpect. p. 122. l. 22. r. the 6th. p. 122. l. 25. r. Sicences. p. 129. l. 14. r. Oppoſition. l. 24. r. Mercury and Mars. p. 131. l. 18. r. oppoſite. p 134. l. dele they. p. 135 l. 8. r. infamous, p. 135. l. 12 dele to. p. 141. l. 13. dele. Oppoſition or. p. 145. l. 21. for quartile Mars p. 147. l. 1. r. great, l. 16. to r. and p. 152. l. 11. r. Courteous. p. 152. l. 13. r. women p. 152. l. ult. r. cruelly. 153. l. r. wickedneſſe.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170163:9"/>
            <head>John Angelus, OF <hi>Aſtrology.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Of the Faces of the Signes, their Significati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp; the Formes of every Degree of the Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diack; with the Condition and Deſcription of the perſon ſignified by them.</head>
               <p>THe firſt Face of <hi>Aries,</hi> is of <hi>Mars,</hi> and it is a Face of Boldneſs, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, Stoutneſſe, and Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty.</p>
               <p>The Second face of <hi>Aries</hi> is of the Sun, and is a Face of Nobility, Highneſſe, Rule and great Dominion.</p>
               <p>The Third Face of <hi>Aries</hi> is of <hi>Venus,</hi> and is a Face of Subtilty in every work, and of Meekneſſe, of Play, Mirth and Beauty.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:170163:10"/>
               <p>In the firſt Face of <hi>Aries,</hi> aſcends a Vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant man Armed, holding out a Fauchion in his right Hand.</p>
               <p>In the Second Face, aſcends a man in a gowne like a Clergy man.</p>
               <p>The third face aſcends like a young woman ſitting on a ſtooll, and playing on a Lute.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The Formes aſcending throughout all the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of <hi>Aries.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In the Firſt degree of ♈, there aſcendeth a man holding a Sicle in in his righ hand, and in his left hand an Engyne of Warre.</p>
                  <p>A man then borne, or querent, ſhall be laboirous, and much exerciſed in War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like affaires.</p>
                  <p>In the Second degree of ♈, there aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man having a Head like a Dog, ſtretching out his right hand towards the Skies, and holding a Staffe in his left hand.</p>
                  <p>It denotes the man borne under that degree, will be a Litigious and trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome perſon and envious as a dog.</p>
                  <p>The Third degree of ♈ ariſeth like a handſome man, ſtretching forth his right hand as if he were ſhewing the various things of the world, and applying his left hand to a girdle bound about him.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170163:10"/>
                  <p>It ſignifies a peaceable quiet perſon.</p>
                  <p>In the Fourth degree of ♈, there aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a man with a curled head of haire, holding a Hawk in his right hand, and a whip in his left hand.</p>
                  <p>The perſon ſignified by this aſcention, is ſeldom rich; but a ſpender of his eſtate, conſuming all he hath in his age.</p>
                  <p>The Firſt degree of <hi>Aries</hi> aſcendeth like two men, one holding in his hand an Axe, cleaving wood; the other, holding a Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in his righthand.</p>
                  <p>It ſignifies a perſon that will be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident houſe-keeper; and a provider for his family.</p>
                  <p>In the ſixth degree of ♈, there aſcends a King Crowned, holding a Globe in his right hand, and a Scepter in his left.</p>
                  <p>The native under this Aſcention, will exceed all his kindred and acquaintance in greatneſſe.</p>
                  <p>The Seventh degree of <hi>Aries</hi> aſcendeth like a man Armed all over, holding a dart in his right hand.</p>
                  <p>It denotes a wary carefull perſon, a preſerver of himſelf.</p>
                  <p>In the eighth degree of <hi>Aries,</hi> there aſcends a man having his head covered with a Helmet, and no where elſe Armed,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170163:11"/>holding in his right hand a Croſſe-bow.</p>
                  <p>Under this degree are ſignified quarrel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome contentious perſons, and Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers.</p>
                  <p>In the Ninth degree of <hi>Aries</hi> there aſcendeth a man bare-headed, well clothed over his body with a Gowne, holding a ſword in his left hand, with the point downwards.</p>
                  <p>It ſignifies talkative perſons full of words, and of a wonderfull Spirit.</p>
                  <p>The Tenth degree of <hi>Aries</hi> ariſeth like a man bare-headed, but clothed over his body, pearcing a Beare thorow, with a ſpeare.</p>
                  <p>It ſignifies a Forreſter or Hunter.</p>
                  <p>In the Eleventh degree of <hi>Aries,</hi> there aſcendeth a woman, ſtanding holding a Diſtaffe in her right hand.</p>
                  <p>It ſignifies Perſons loving freind-ſhip and hoſpitality.</p>
                  <p>In the Twelfth degree of <hi>Aries</hi> there aſcendeth an Eagle, ſpreading out her wings over her young-ones, ſitting under her.</p>
                  <p>It denotes ambitious perſons, Proud, Covetuous of applauſe, and aſpiring to be exalted to dignity.</p>
                  <p>The Thirteenth degree of <hi>Aries</hi> aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170163:11"/>like a ſubtil perſon with his right hand, holding a Goate by the horns.</p>
                  <p>The Perſon borne under him, will be wonderfull famous.</p>
                  <p>The 14. Degree of <hi>Aries</hi> ariſeth like a Captived man ſtanding upright between two pillars having his Armes bound with two Chains.</p>
                  <p>It denotes perſons much Subject to Impriſonment.</p>
                  <p>The 15. Degree of <hi>Aries</hi> aſcendeth like a man bare-headed, his armes ſtretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out, and cloathed with an <hi>Habergeon:</hi> it Signifies theeves, retchleſſe, leud, and wicked perſons.</p>
                  <p>In the 16. Degree, of <hi>Aries</hi> ariſeth a man labouring with a dungfork; or ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times a man powring water out of a pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</p>
                  <p>it denotes a Fiſher-man or a Labourer.</p>
                  <p>The 17. Degree ariſeth like a man ſtanding Idle, Clothed in fine ſilke.</p>
                  <p>It Repreſents fine delicate perſons.</p>
                  <p>In the 18. Degree, aſcends a woman ſitting on a Chair, holding up her right hand: it denotes a man Loving peace and quietneſſe.</p>
                  <p>In the 19. Degree of <hi>Aries,</hi> aſcends a man cloath'd with an <hi>Habergeon</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:170163:12"/>ſtanding &amp; ſhewing treaſure and money with his hands.</p>
                  <p>A Theefe, Wicked, debauched perſon, is ſignified by this Degree.</p>
                  <p>In the 20. Degree of <hi>Aries,</hi> aſcendeth a man with a Helmet on his head, and an Oſtrith-Feather in his Hat; Riding upon a Bull, Leading a horſe in his Left-hand.</p>
                  <p>The man born under this Degree, will be malicious.</p>
                  <p>The 21. Degree of <hi>Aries</hi> aſcendeth a dog ſitting and turning his face towards a Lyon.</p>
                  <p>It Signifies a faithfull Companion.</p>
                  <p>In the 22. Degree of <hi>Aries,</hi> ariſeth a Bear, ſitting and holding a great Beame in his mouth.</p>
                  <p>The man will be a wicked perſon that is ſignified hereby.</p>
                  <p>In the 23. Degree of <hi>Aries,</hi> there aſcendeth 6. Serpents, three of them fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the other three.</p>
                  <p>The man, then born, will have many enemies.</p>
                  <p>In the 24. Degree there aſcendeth a naked woman, Covering her ſecrets with her left-hand, and holding up her right-hand.</p>
                  <p>If the native be a woman, ſhee will be
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170163:12"/>deſirous of a man; If a man, much given to women.</p>
                  <p>In the 25. Degree of <hi>Aries,</hi> ariſeth a man with Curled locks, Riding upon a Ram, holding him by the horns.</p>
                  <p>It Signifies a Citizen covetous to beare rule.</p>
                  <p>The 26. Degree ariſeth 2. Suns, one ſhining againſt the other.</p>
                  <p>A man bearing rule and keeping his power, is Signified hereby.</p>
                  <p>The 27. Degree aſcendeth like a great Dragon, lying upon the earth.</p>
                  <p>A man that will be potent in his old age is Signified by this aſcenſion.</p>
                  <p>In the 28. degree of <hi>Aries</hi> aſcendeth a woman ſtanding upright, being well cloth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
                  <p>It ſignifies a pleaſant peaceable perſon.</p>
                  <p>In the 29. degree ariſeth a Man hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Saw in his hands.</p>
                  <p>A laborious perſon nouriſhing himſelf and his Wife by his labour, is ſignified hereby.</p>
                  <p>In the 30. degree of ♈, aſcendeth an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtere Woman, leading a ſadled horſe in her right hand.</p>
                  <p>The native under this degree, will be high-minded, ambitious to beare rule over others.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:170163:13"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of Taurus.</head>
               <p>THe firſt face of <hi>Taurus,</hi> is the face of ☿ and it is a face of Plowing, Sowing, building, peopling-houſes, of learning and wiſdom in the earth, and of learning in Geometry.</p>
               <p>The 2. is the face of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> and it is a face of Power, Nobility, Dignity, and neceſſity over people.</p>
               <p>The third face is of ♈, &amp; it is face of mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, ſlavery, madneſs, neceſſity &amp; baſeneſſe.</p>
               <p>In the firſt face <hi>Taurus,</hi> aſcends a book, a young man tilling of the ground.</p>
               <p>In the Second a tall man girt with a girdle, holding a Key in his right hand.</p>
               <p>In the Third a decrepit old man lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a Crutch, hanging down one Arme, and having a wodden leg.</p>
               <p>In the Firſt degree of ♉, aſcendeth a man leading a Bull to the ſlaughter, holding a Staffe in his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Hangman.</p>
               <p>In the Second degree of ♉ ariſeth a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man holding a horſe-tayle in her hand.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:170163:13"/>
               <p>It denotes an idle perſon.</p>
               <p>In the Third degree aſcendeth an old Woman naked covering her <hi>pudenda</hi> with her left hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Woman deſirous of a man in her old age, and to continue young.</p>
               <p>In the Fourth, a Woman holding a whip in her right hand.</p>
               <p>In denotes a haſty angry perſon.</p>
               <p>In the Fifth degree of ♉, ariſeth a Bull ſitting in a Chaldron.</p>
               <p>By this aſcention are ſignified men lov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hoſpitality, good houſe-keepers.</p>
               <p>In the ſixth degree aſcends a man having three heads, and pointing to the ground with his right hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a prudent wiſe and illuſtrious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the Seventh degree, ariſes a beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull woman ſtanding naked.</p>
               <p>It denores a man of a proud mind.</p>
               <p>In the Eighth degree of ♉, aſcends a ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowfull Woman ſitting upon a footſtoole.</p>
               <p>It fignifies a man of a low humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected Spirit.</p>
               <p>In the 9. degree of ♉, ariſeth a man holding a whip in his hand feeding Sheep and Goats in a field.</p>
               <p>The man then borne will be a Neat-herd or Shephard.</p>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:170163:14"/>
               <p>In the 10 degree of ♉, aſcendeth two men ſtanding, with a Dog playing between them.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies an idle perſon, much addicted to venereous acts.</p>
               <p>In the 11. degree, ariſeth a Crow ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the ground.</p>
               <p>It demonſtrates a covetuous perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 12. degree, ariſe, two women ſtanding hand in hand.</p>
               <p>It imports a benevolent well minded man.</p>
               <p>In the 13. degree of ♉, ſcends two Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men with Staves, ſmiting and ſtriking one another.</p>
               <p>It denotes a troubleſome, contentions, wrangling perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 14. degree ariſeth a man hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Staffe in his hand: hereby is ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied an appeaſer of quarels, or one reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and bridling the contentious.</p>
               <p>In the 15. degree, aſcend 7. fowls, fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Aire.</p>
               <p>It Signifies an inſtable wavering minded man.</p>
               <p>In the 16. degree, aſcends a man riding on an Aſſe.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Sluggard, a man ſlow and tedious in all his actions.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:170163:14"/>
               <p>In the 17. degreeof ♉, ariſeth a Bull bound by the middle to a tree.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man much over-laden with daily labour.</p>
               <p>In the 18. degree aſcends two Bulls fighting one againſt another.</p>
               <p>It denotes a raging furious man.</p>
               <p>In the 19. degree, aſcends a Woman powring water out of one pot into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a ſmooth tongued perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 20. degree of ♉, aſcends two Dogs, a fighting.</p>
               <p>It demonſtrates an envious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 21. degree, there ariſeth a Beare looking backwards.</p>
               <p>In ſignifies a wicked, malitious, and wrathfull perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 22. degree, aſcend three men holding one another by the hands: the perſon ſignified hereby, will be a lover of peace and friend-ſhip.</p>
               <p>In the 23. degree aſcends a man falling backwards to the earth.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies, a man unfortunate in all things.</p>
               <p>In the 24. degree of ♉, aſcends a crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man holding himſelf up upon his ſtaffe.</p>
               <p>It denotes a perſon weak and feeble in his Actions.</p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:170163:15"/>
               <p>In the 25. degree, a man ſtanding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right, and holding a Staffe in his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a valiant man, ſtrong and powerfull in his deeds.</p>
               <p>In the 26. degree, a man ſtanding ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his hand.</p>
               <p>A peaceable perſon, or a peace-maker is hereby ſignified.</p>
               <p>In the 27. degree, there ariſeth the ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of a field of wheate or Corne ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing un-cut.</p>
               <p>This aſcention denotes a gatherer toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and heaper up of riches.</p>
               <p>In the 28. degree, a Woman leading a horſe by the bridle.</p>
               <p>It denotes a perſon deſirous to rule o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver others.</p>
               <p>In the 29. degree, there aſcendeth a Woman leading an Aſſe with a Bridle, or otherwiſe a Woman leading a he-Goate by the Horns.</p>
               <p>Hereby is ſignified a Woman that rules over her Husband.</p>
               <p>In the 30. degree of ♉, there aſcends a faire beautifull building.</p>
               <p>Hereby is ſignified a perſon delighting to do pleaſant and delectable deeds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:170163:15"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of Gemini.</head>
               <p>THe firſt face of ♊ is of ♃, and is a face of writing, of giving and receiving mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, of petition, and wiſdom in unprofi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table things.</p>
               <p>The 2. face is of ♂ and is a face of burd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, preſſure, labour, and getting goods by labour, and of unhoneſt actions.</p>
               <p>The 3. face is of the Sun, and is a face of oblivion, diſdaine, of mirth and jollity, and of hearing unprofitable words.</p>
               <p>The firſt face aſcendeth like a young man girt with a girdle.</p>
               <p>The ſecond like a man with an axe cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting wood.</p>
               <p>The third, a man with a Hawk in his right hand, and a pipe in his left.</p>
               <p>In the 1. degree of ♊, aſcendeth two men ſitting on the ground holding one another by the hands.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a joyfull merry man.</p>
               <p>In the 2. degree of ♊, there aſcends one
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170163:16"/>man girt with a ſword, leading two other naked men bound.</p>
               <p>The perſon hereby ſignifyed, will be a Jaylor, or Theefe-taker.</p>
               <p>In the 3. degree, ariſeth a man ſinging and playing on a Lute.</p>
               <p>It denotes a man, cauſing joy to others.</p>
               <p>In the 4. degree, aſcends a man lead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Wife by the hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies, one keeping good hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and entertainment for others.</p>
               <p>It the 5. Degree a man holding a Croſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bow in his left hand, and a girdle in his right.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man preparing for war.</p>
               <p>In the 6. a man holding a ballance in his right-hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Marchant.</p>
               <p>In the 7. two brides, hand in hand.</p>
               <p>It denores a perſon, imployed in nupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all affairs.</p>
               <p>In the 8. Degree, aſcends a Smith Smite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Iron, and a woman ſtanding by Idle.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a perſon ſhunning labour, and loving Idleneſſe.</p>
               <p>In the 9. Degree of ♊ aſcends a king fitting on a throne, having a Globe in his right-hand and a Scepter in his left.</p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:170163:16"/>
               <p>Signifing a man ſhall have great power and Authority, that is born under this degree.</p>
               <p>In the 10. Degree, a man aſcends lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up another man from the ground.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a perſon compoſing differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, freindlily, a mongſt others.</p>
               <p>In the 11. an Eagle fluttering with her wings over three of her young ones.</p>
               <p>The man will be a South-ſayer, or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurer that is Signified hereby.</p>
               <p>In the 12. Degree, ariſe two women ſtanding weeping.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a Sorrowfull perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 13. three Crownes ſtanding toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther on the ground.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Covetous and Envious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>In the 14. aſcends two Foxes devour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Henns.</p>
               <p>The man born under this degree, will be a glutton and Covetous.</p>
               <p>In the 15. aſcends a man having three heads.</p>
               <p>It Signifies one of good underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>The 16. aſcends like a Bridge beſide the water.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a man labouring without profit.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:170163:17"/>
               <p>In the 17. Degree of ♊, aſcends a man without hands, and Idle.</p>
               <p>It Signifies an unprofitable perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 18. degree, a Fox running Swift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Laborious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 19. Degree aſcends a poor man carrying a Staffe on his ſhoulder.</p>
               <p>It Signifies the man will be a travailer, a foot-poſt.</p>
               <p>In the 20. Degree, three Snakes lying on the ground</p>
               <p>The man born under this degree, will be wiſe and of good underſtanding.</p>
               <p>In the 21. Degree, aſcends a man ſitting on Horſe Back.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Clyent or one retayning to another to have his Defence</p>
               <p>In the 22. aſcend two Birds Chattering together.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a fowler.</p>
               <p>In the 23. Degree a decrepit old man leaning on a ſtaffe.</p>
               <p>It demon Strates a poor miſerable Idle perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 24. two women ſitting at play together.</p>
               <p>It repreſents one given to mirth.</p>
               <p>In the 25. Degree, a man holding a book open in his hand.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:170163:17"/>
               <p>It denotes a ſtudious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 26. of ♊, aſcend two Doge fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>it repreſents a quarelſome litigious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 27. Degree, a woman aſcends ſtanding idle and weeping.</p>
               <p>An idle vagabond is hereby ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>In the 28. Degree, aſcend two Bulls due greater then other.</p>
               <p>A Laborious man is hereby repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>In the 29. Degree, aſcend 3. Doggs, 2. running one way together, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the contrary way.</p>
               <p>The man thereby Signified will be a Huntsman to ſome Noble Man.</p>
               <p>In the 30. Degree, aſcend 2. men, each of them leading a Hound in a Chain.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a Huntsman of a Prince.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:170163:18"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Of Cancer.</head>
               <p>THe firſt face of ♋ is of ♀, and is a face of joy, Subtilty, Humanity, Couneſie, and of ſuch things as induce men to love.</p>
               <p>The Second face of ♋ is of ☿, and is a face of Jollity, Mirch, of women, of rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and plenty.</p>
               <p>The Third face of ♋ is of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> and is a face of Hunting, purſuing Fugitives; of getting goods by war, quarrells and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention amongſt men.</p>
               <p>The Firſt face of ♋ appeareth like a beautifull woman holding a Flower in her hand.</p>
               <p>The Second face, a man and a woman ſitting at a table with great heaps of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney before them.</p>
               <p>The Third face, a Hunter blowing a Horn with a Dog by his ſide, and a ſpear on his ſhoulder.</p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:170163:18"/>
               <p>In the firſt degree of ♋, aſcendeth a man and a woman holding one another by the hands and rejoycing.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies an Amiable perſon given to mirth.</p>
               <p>In the Second Degree, aſcends 2. wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſtanding Idle, like 2. Turrets.</p>
               <p>The man ſignified hereby will be Idle.</p>
               <p>In the Third Degree, ariſes two women Sitting, and tow men ſtanding before them.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a ſerving man, one wayring upon anothers pleaſure.</p>
               <p>In the 4. a maide ſtanding Idle, expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a man.</p>
               <p>It repreſents a libidinous perſon full of luſtfull thoughts.</p>
               <p>In the 5. a woman ſtanding expecting a man.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Luxurious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 6. a man holding a Goat in a Braſſe pot.</p>
               <p>It denotes a fool.</p>
               <p>In the 7. a man leading a goate with a girdle about his horns.</p>
               <p>A Hangman is hereby Signified.</p>
               <p>In the 8. Degree of ♋, aſcends a houſe, and a woman ſtanding as it were abſcond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her ſelf behind it.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:170163:19"/>
               <p>It Signifies a Lazy, ſlow, and laſcivious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 9. a woman holding a diſtaff in her right hand.</p>
               <p>It imports a laborious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 10. a man holding a Cheſt in his right hand.</p>
               <p>It Signifies alſo a laborious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 11. a ſhip ſtanding in the water</p>
               <p>It repreſents a fiſher-man.</p>
               <p>In the 12. a man carrying the skin of a Beaſt on his ſhoulders.</p>
               <p>A Cobler or Currier, or ſuch handi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft, is hereby ſignified.</p>
               <p>In the 13. a Boy ſitting holding a Book open, with a pen in his hand.</p>
               <p>It repreſents a ſtudious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 14. a Lambe aſcends having a Crown of Gold on his head.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a Gold Smith.</p>
               <p>In the 15. aſcends a horſe and a mouſe lying in her neſt under the roofe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</p>
               <p>It repreſents a man deſirous to keep home.</p>
               <p>In the 16. a bird holding a Serpent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der her feet.</p>
               <p>It imports a man accounting himſelf Noble.</p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:170163:19"/>
               <p>In the 17. Degree, a woman ſtanding idle aſcends.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a ſluggiſh perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 18. Degree of ♋ aſcends 3. women ſitting at play at Tables.</p>
               <p>A joyfull merry perſon it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents.</p>
               <p>In the 19. Degree, a man having a Spear in his right hand, and a pipe in his left.</p>
               <p>A ſtage player is hereby Signified.</p>
               <p>In the 20. a Dog ſitting in a Chariot.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a ſlothfull perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 21. a Chariot ſtanding empty.</p>
               <p>It denotes a perſon given to vanity.</p>
               <p>In the 22. aſcends a man ſtanding idle.</p>
               <p>it ſignifies a ſlothfull perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 23. aſcends a running water.</p>
               <p>An inſtable unconſtant perſon is Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied under this Degree.</p>
               <p>In the 24. aſcends 2. Horſes, one leap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon the others back.</p>
               <p>It repreſents a man of aſpiring thoughts Coveting dignity and authority over o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>In the 25. a Horſe running in a field.</p>
               <p>It Signifies an inſtable perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 26. Degree, a water Springing out of mountaines.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:170163:20"/>
               <p>It ſignifies a moveable unſtable man.</p>
               <p>In the 27. a Horſe bridled.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man in bondage and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitude.</p>
               <p>In the 28. degree of ♋, aſcends two men fitting under a tree, and ſeeing a Hawke in the tree.</p>
               <p>It denotes an idle perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 29. a man hanging on the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Theefe.</p>
               <p>In the 30. degree of ♋, a Ship Sailing on the water.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Saylour or Marriner.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Of</hi> Leo.</head>
               <p>TThe firſt face of Leo is of ♏ and is a face of cruelty, wickedneſſe, and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, of ſuſteyning great labours, boldneſſe, and luſt.</p>
               <p>The ſecond face is of ♃ and is a face of wrangling, quarrelling, ignorance, neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity; of victory over the miſerable and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:170163:20"/>vile, through their ignorance; of occaſion of drawing ſwords and Warrs.</p>
               <p>The third face is of <hi>Mars,</hi> and is a face of love, ſociety, not parting from, not looſing of ones own, for avoiding quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels:</p>
               <p>The 1. face aſcends like a Man riding on a Lyon, with a feather in his hat.</p>
               <p>The 2. a man holding a ſword drawne over his head in one hand, and a buckler in the other.</p>
               <p>the 3. a young man with a Hawk on his fiſt.</p>
               <p>In the 1. degree of <hi>Leo,</hi> there aſcends a man holding a Lyons head in his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a valiant man.</p>
               <p>In the 2. degree, aſcends a Ship, one ſide thereof inclining towards the waters.</p>
               <p>The man will be unfortunate in the water, that is ſignified hereby.</p>
               <p>In the 3. degree, a man aſcends ſitting mourning upon a foot-ſtool.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a ſorrowfull perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 4. degree, a Fiſh ſwimming in the water.</p>
               <p>A prudent and a crafty perſon is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſignified, affected of great men.</p>
               <p>In the 5. a Serpent lying wreathed on the ground.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:170163:21"/>
               <p>It ſignifies an envious man.</p>
               <p>In the 6. a man holding a ſword drawn in his right hand.</p>
               <p>A litigious perſon deſirous to reſiſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers is ſignified by this degree.</p>
               <p>Iu the 7. degree ariſeth a man riding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Lyon.</p>
               <p>A valiant man, ſtrong and wiſe is by this aſcention denoted.</p>
               <p>In the 8. a fire flaming.</p>
               <p>It imports a labourer with fire.</p>
               <p>In the 9 a man well clothed and adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a proud man.</p>
               <p>In the 10. death ſtanding with a Syth in his hands.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a murtherer.</p>
               <p>In the 11. degree of ♌ aſcends a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſtanding and ſhewing her naked bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</p>
               <p>It demonſtrates an impudent immodeſt perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 12. A beautifull woman aſcends well adorned.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a chaſt modeſt perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 13. a Bull feeding in paſture.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man conſtant and ſtable in his deeds.</p>
               <p>In the 14. a man ſtanding idle ariſeth.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:170163:21"/>
               <p>It ſignifies a loyterer.</p>
               <p>In the 15. degree a Dog or Lyon lying couched in the graſſe.</p>
               <p>A valiant man is hereby repreſented.</p>
               <p>In the 16. a bridled Aſſe.</p>
               <p>An illiterate dull perſon it ſignifies.</p>
               <p>In the 17. aſcends a Cammel ſtanding.</p>
               <p>The perſon hereby ſignified will be valiant and full of Spirit.</p>
               <p>In the 18. a Key of a Chamber.</p>
               <p>A man of power it imports.</p>
               <p>In the 19. a man leading a horſe by the bridle,</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a clyent or one pertaining to a noble man.</p>
               <p>In the 20. a man holding role of paper in hishand.</p>
               <p>A Meſſenger or Carryer it ſignifies.</p>
               <p>In the 21. a man holding a. Key in his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a keeper of good hoſpitali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</p>
               <p>In the 22. a man lying as if he were dead.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a weak feeble perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 23. degree of ♌ aſcends a man having two heads.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man of ſeverall mindes.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:170163:22"/>
               <p>In the 24. a man holding a lock in his' right-hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man meditating wiſdom.</p>
               <p>In the 25. a man ſwimming in the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>It denotes a fiſherman.</p>
               <p>In the 26. a man working with a dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forke.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a labourer.</p>
               <p>In the 27. a man holding a ſicle in his right hand.</p>
               <p>A laborious perſon it repreſents.</p>
               <p>In the 28. three men ſporting together.</p>
               <p>It repreſents an idle fellow.</p>
               <p>In the 29. a man and woman holding one another by the hands.</p>
               <p>An Amiable perſon is hereby ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>In the 30. degree of ♌ aſcends a ſervant riding on a horſe.</p>
               <p>The man by this aſcention ſignified will be a ſervant unto others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:170163:22"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Of</hi> Virgo.</head>
               <p>THe firſt face of ♍ is of the Sun, and is a face of ſowing, plowing, of planting herbs, peopling, gathering together riches and food.</p>
               <p>The ſecond face is of ♀, and is a face of gaine, of getting ſubſtance, covetuouſly rak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together, and being covetuous, and ariſing with the ſtrength of men.</p>
               <p>The third face of ♍, is of ☿ and is a face of old age, of debility, ſlothfullneſſe, and of loſſe of the members through in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities; of pulling up trees, and depopu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating of places peopled.</p>
               <p>In the firſt face of ♍ aſcends a man lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing money into a Cheſt.</p>
               <p>In the 2. two men one having a purſe in his hand.</p>
               <p>In the 3. a decrepit old man leaning on a ſtaffe.</p>
               <p>In the 1. degree of ♍, aſcends a woman adorned expecting the ſight of a man.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:170163:23"/>
               <p>It ſignifies a lover, either man or wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</p>
               <p>In the 2. degree aſcends two women ſtanding idle.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a vagabond and idle per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>In the 3. a man holding a booke of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts in his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Merchant.</p>
               <p>In the 4. a man at plow with Oxen.</p>
               <p>A labourer in the field is hereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noted.</p>
               <p>In the 5. an Eagle reſting.</p>
               <p>A Merchant, but one living without labour, is hereby demonſtrated.</p>
               <p>In the 6. a Woman well clothed ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing idle.</p>
               <p>An idle fellow it ſignifies.</p>
               <p>In the 7. a ſimple woman ſtanding idle.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a ſluggiſh perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 8. a man ſitting under a tree.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Shepheard.</p>
               <p>In the 9. degree of ♍, aſcends a woman well clothed, with a red face ſtanding i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle.</p>
               <p>The man hereby ſignified will be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and luxurious.</p>
               <p>In the 10, a man well c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>othed ſtanding
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170163:23"/>idle holding an apple in his hand.</p>
               <p>It intimates a vagabond or wanderer-about.</p>
               <p>In the 11. a white horſe bridled running.</p>
               <p>The man hereby ſignified will be ſwift a fo<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>In the 12. a man in red clothes, with a black face.</p>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wicked perſon it repreſents.</p>
               <p>In the 2. degree, aſcend two women gathering roſes.</p>
               <p>A merry jocund man it denotes.</p>
               <p>In the 14. an Oxe ſtanding in paſture.</p>
               <p>The man borne under this degree will be laborious.</p>
               <p>In the 15. two merry women ſtanding together.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a merry perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 16. aſcends two Dogs running. together.</p>
               <p>The man having this degree aſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, will be a Huntſman.</p>
               <p>In the 17. A faire Caſtle compaſſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with a Hedge.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man living in ſafety.</p>
               <p>In the 18. degree, ariſeth a tree full of leaves ſtanding in Graſſe.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies, the man will be a labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer in woods:</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:170163:24"/>
               <p>In the 19. a man ſitting as a ſervant up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Horſe.</p>
               <p>The man will be a reteyner to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>In the 20. degree of ♍, ariſeth a Bird following a Mole or a Mouſe.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man contrary to others.</p>
               <p>In the 21. a man ariſeth ſtanding and holding Gold in his right hand, and ſilver in his left.</p>
               <p>A rich man it ſignifies.</p>
               <p>In the 22. a naked woman carrying a Goat and a Lamb on her ſhoulders.</p>
               <p>An impudent immodeſt perſon it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes.</p>
               <p>In the 23. A man aſcends rowing a boat in the water with an Oare.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Marriner.</p>
               <p>In the 24. A Bird bound by the neck to a poſt.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man who will be reſtrayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and held to labour.</p>
               <p>In the 25. a man caſting a ſtone into a ditch.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a litigious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 26. two men diſcourſing toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies the man will be well educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170163:24"/>
               <p>In the 27. two women ſtanding idle.</p>
               <p>An idle perſon is denoted.</p>
               <p>In the 28. degree aſcends ſome on the ground, others flying in the Aire.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies the man ſhall have much Rents.</p>
               <p>In the 29. aſcends dew or raine falling on the ground.</p>
               <p>The perſon will be religious that is ſignified by it.</p>
               <p>In the 30. degree, aſcends a dumb man ſtanding ſtill.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a foole.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Of</hi> Libra.</head>
               <p>THe firſt face of <hi>Libra</hi> is of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, and is a face of Juſtice right and truth, of ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couring the weake againſt the ſtrong &amp; the wicked, &amp; of helping the poore &amp; miſerable</p>
               <p>The ſecond is of <hi>Saturn,</hi> and is a face of quietneſſe, plenty, and good life, quiet and ſecure.</p>
               <p>The third face is of ♃, and is a face of gluttony, of ſodomy, of ſinging, and mirth
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170163:25"/>and following evil pleaſures.</p>
               <p>In the firſt face of ♎, aſcendeth a ſtudent having a book open before him.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond, an old man in a Gowne ſitting in a Chaire.</p>
               <p>In the third, a young man having a cup in his hand.</p>
               <p>In the 1. degree of ♎, aſcendeth a man holding in each hand a ſpeare.</p>
               <p>The man who hath this aſcendent will be a Warriour.</p>
               <p>In the 2. degree a Clergy man with a pot of incenſe.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a religious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 3. degree a decrepit man crooked in his hands and feet.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies amiſerable laborious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 4. a man at plow with horſes.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a labourer in the fields.</p>
               <p>In the 5. a black-bird, with red bill &amp; feet.</p>
               <p>It denotes a fat groſſe man.</p>
               <p>In the 6. a man drawing a plow himſelf.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man taking a great deale of paines without ſence or reaſon.</p>
               <p>In the 7. degree of ♎, a man holding a Gold Ring in his right hand.</p>
               <p>The perſon is ſignified to be a lover.</p>
               <p>In the 8. a woman weeping over one that is ſick.</p>
               <p>It repreſents a ſorrowfull man.</p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:170163:25"/>
               <p>In the 9. a man holding a ſword over this head in his right hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a litigious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 10. a black-bird holding his beak to the ground.</p>
               <p>The man is ſignified to be altogether a ſloven.</p>
               <p>In the 11. degree a man with black hands and face, but white feet.</p>
               <p>It denotes an idle, dull; but unſtable perſon</p>
               <p>In the 12. a woman ſtanding looking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her.</p>
               <p>The man having this aſcendant will be a vagabond and idle.</p>
               <p>In the 13. degree a man and a woman going two ſeverall wayes.</p>
               <p>The man having this degree riſing, wil be contentious, &amp; live divided from others.</p>
               <p>In the 14. a great looking glaſſe fixed upon a wall.</p>
               <p>It denotes a proud perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 15. two hearts hanging together.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a wordling.</p>
               <p>In the 16. camell running: It ſignifies the man will be ſwift and valiant.</p>
               <p>In the 17. a bird ſweetly ſinging.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a perſon full of mirth.</p>
               <p>In the 18. degree of <hi>Libra,</hi> aſcends the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170163:26"/>ſimilitude of a Village neatly built.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man having dominion in the Country.</p>
               <p>In the 19. degree a faire Caſtle on a Mountayne.</p>
               <p>It denotes a noble man.</p>
               <p>In the 20. degree, a faire Altar beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully Adorned.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies, a religious man.</p>
               <p>In the 21. degree, a man riding on an Aſſe or Horſe.</p>
               <p>The man will be a Horſeman, a groome and ſervant, who hath this degree riſing. In the 22. degree, aſcends 2. horſes ſadled.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man coveting much and enjoying little.</p>
               <p>In the 23. degree, a phyſitian viewing an Urinal through a glaſſe.</p>
               <p>The man will be a phyſitian, who is ſignified hereby.</p>
               <p>In the 24. degree, aſcends a man in the upper part, and a horſe in the lower parts beating a Dragon with a Staffe.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a ſtrong man.</p>
               <p>In the 25. degree, a Peacock ſtanding in the Graſſe.</p>
               <p>It imports a proud perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 26. degree, aſcends a man beat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Lyon with a ſtaffe.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies, he will be a Conquerer in Warre.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:170163:26"/>
               <p>In the 27. degree a ſhady tree ſtanding in a garden.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies the man to be a gardiner.</p>
               <p>In the 28. degree aſcends a man labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a ſpade.</p>
               <p>A laborious perſon, it repreſents,</p>
               <p>In the 29. degree, a woman ſtanding i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies an idle perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 30. degree of <hi>Libra,</hi> aſcends a Hare running out of a wood.</p>
               <p>The man hereby ſignified will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant and unſtable.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Of Scorpio.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe firſt face of ♏ is of ♂, and is a face of ſtrife, ſadneſſe, deceipt, detraction, perdition and treachery.</p>
               <p>The ſecond face of ♏, is of the ☉, and is a face of affronts, detections, ſtirring up miſchieſs and quarrels betweene men and continuing that ſtrife which it ſtireth up.</p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:170163:27"/>
               <p>The third face is of ♀, and is a face of Warre, Drunkenneſſe, and Violence, Fornication, Wrath and Pride.</p>
               <p>In the firſt face appeares two men a fighting and tearing one another by the haire.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond, a man ſitting on a ſtoole, and two dogs a fighting by him.</p>
               <p>In the third, two women pulling one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother by the haire of the head, one hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a ſtaffe in her right hand, ſtriking the other on the head.</p>
               <p>In the 1. degree of ♏, appeareth a man holding a ſpeare in his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a theefe and a wicked fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.</p>
               <p>In the 2. aſcends a man riding upon an Elephant.</p>
               <p>It denotes a ſtrong valiant and ſtable perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 3. a man ſtanding idle.</p>
               <p>It declares the perſon to be wicked and idle.</p>
               <p>In the 4. a man playing on a Harpe.</p>
               <p>It denotes a jocond merry man.</p>
               <p>In the 5. degree, a man aſcends, wanting the lower part of his body.</p>
               <p>The man will be imperfect in his deeds.</p>
               <p>In the 6. degree an Aſſe or Horſe brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170163:27"/>and ſadled.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a man producing few things to good effect.</p>
               <p>In the 7. degree aſcends a man ſitting and having a purſe of money in his right hand, and in his left hand a golden cup,.</p>
               <p>It denotes a rich marchant.</p>
               <p>In the 8. a great Cock ſtanding.</p>
               <p>The man will be a Scrivener.</p>
               <p>In the 9. a man ſitting in a Tub.</p>
               <p>It denotes one of litle wit.</p>
               <p>In the 10. degree, aſcends a head with a face much wrinkled.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a man of ſtrange opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>In the 11. degree a man holding a Scorpion by the neck.</p>
               <p>It Signifies an envious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 12. Degree of ♍ ariſeth a great Serpent with three Flyes biting of her.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a wiſe man, but wicked.</p>
               <p>In the 13. Degree. a fair and ſtrong Tower.</p>
               <p>The man will be a ſtrong labourer.</p>
               <p>In the 14. Degree, a well without wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a man inſtable without wit.</p>
               <p>In the 15. Degree, a fair woman ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing idle.</p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170163:28"/>
               <p>It denotes an idle perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 16. degree a woman giving Almes to a poor man.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a mercifull man.</p>
               <p>In 17. degree, a wolfe running in a field.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Robber.</p>
               <p>In the 18. a houſe, and woman hiding her ſelf behind the door.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a ſluggiſh idle perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 19. a dog with great mouth and eares.</p>
               <p>It repreſents a Noble man.</p>
               <p>It the 20. a man ſitting on a Camel.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a valiant man.</p>
               <p>In the 21. degree aſcends a horſe ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing freely in a field.</p>
               <p>It Signifies the man ſhall not be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to the yoak of others.</p>
               <p>In the 22. Degree a great floud of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               <p>An inſtable perſon is thereby denoted.</p>
               <p>In the 23. Degree, many rivers flowing out of a fountaine.</p>
               <p>It Signifies an unſtable unconſtant per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>In the 24. Deg. of ♏ aſcends a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man holding a diſtaff in her right hand.</p>
               <p>It denotes a laborious man.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:170163:28"/>
               <p>In the 25. a wolf Carrying a foul in his mouth.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a theef and a robber.</p>
               <p>In the 26. Deg. a man carrying gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſpoyled on his ſhoulders.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a deſtroyer.</p>
               <p>In the 27. ariſe two men ſtanding ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a Jocound ſociable perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 28. deg. a houſe or great Church aſcends.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a man much given to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
               <p>In the 29. deg. a Maſter ſitting with a Book open.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a ſtudious man.</p>
               <p>In the 30. Degree, aſcends a Serpent with a great head.</p>
               <p>A prudent perſon is thereby Signifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:170163:29"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Of Sagitary.</head>
               <p>THe firſt face of ♓ is of ☿, and is a face of Boldneſs, freedom, and warfar.</p>
               <p>The Second is of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, and is a face of feare, of lamentation, griefe, and of a fearefull Spirit over his own body.</p>
               <p>The third is of ♄ and is a face of willful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and not being perſwaded from it, of contrarying, yeilding, agility in evil, ſtrife and horrible things.</p>
               <p>In the firſt face aſcendeth a man armed with a polax in his hand.</p>
               <p>In the Second, a man ſitting, mourning on a ſtool.</p>
               <p>In the third a man with a feather in his hat, holding a ſtaffe on the top of his fing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
               <p>In the firſt Degree of ♓, aſcend three men ſtanding without heads.</p>
               <p>The man hereby Signified will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious and juſt.</p>
               <p>In the Second Degree a man aſcends
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170163:29"/>ſhooting an arrow out of a Croſſe-Bow.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a perſon alwayes litigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <p>In the 3. a man ſitting on a Ram, cleathed with flame.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a litigious troubleſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>In the 4. a man carrying a ſpeare on his ſhoulder.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a deſtroyer.</p>
               <p>In the 5. aſcends a woman carrying a Cradle on her ſhoulder.</p>
               <p>It denotes a laborious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 5. an ox with three horns.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a man of good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</p>
               <p>In the 7. degree a woman ſtanding Idle.</p>
               <p>The man hereby Signified will be an Idle perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 8. Degree, two men playing at Dice upon a table.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a player.</p>
               <p>In the 9. Degree, a great fire of wood burning.</p>
               <p>It denotes the man will be a labourer with fire.</p>
               <p>In the 10. aſcends a portion of gold and ſilver in the earth.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:170163:30"/>
               <p>It Signifies a rich man.</p>
               <p>In the 11. Degree, an ape ſitting upon a Wolfe.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a ruler over another man.</p>
               <p>In the 12. a man riding upon a goat.</p>
               <p>It ſiignifies A contrarier of others.</p>
               <p>In 13. Degree, aſcends a man having his hands bound behind him.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a conquered vanquiſht man.</p>
               <p>In the 14. a maſter holding a Book o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen.</p>
               <p>The man hereby Signified will be learned.</p>
               <p>In the 15. Degree, a man walking by a horſe ſadled.</p>
               <p>It Signif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es a fearfull Coward.</p>
               <p>In the 16. Degree, aſcend Chariot-wheels without the body.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a man void of reaſon.</p>
               <p>In the 17. Degree, a decrepit perſon lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on a ſtaffe.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a man much given to pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
               <p>In the 18. Degree, a man holding a bird by the tayl, and in the other hand a burning torch.</p>
               <p>It Signifies the man will be a fowler.</p>
               <p>It the 19. Degree, aſcends a houſe
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170163:30"/>Compaſſed about with burning faggots.</p>
               <p>The man thereby Signified will be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious and compaſſed about with fear.</p>
               <p>In the 20. Degree, three men walking leading one another by the armes.</p>
               <p>It Signifies one merry and ſociable.</p>
               <p>In the 21. Degree a man ſtanding in the habit of a Doctor.</p>
               <p>It denotes a wiſe man.</p>
               <p>In the 22. degree two men piercing one another with their ſwords.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a theefe and manſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</p>
               <p>In the 23. degree a woman cutting another in the Breaſt with a knife.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a manſlayer.</p>
               <p>In the 24. degree, aſcends a man run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning himſelf through with a ſword.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man that will be his own enemy.</p>
               <p>In the 25. degree. A man vomiting upon the ground.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Drunkard, yet a laborlous man.</p>
               <p>In the 26. degree. A man playing with a little ſtaſſe.</p>
               <p>The man will be a ſtage player, a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perſon that is hereby denoted.</p>
               <p>In the 27. degree. A man hanging with his hands on a beame.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170163:31"/>
               <p>It denotes a merry fellow.</p>
               <p>In the 28. degree. A man riding on a Camel aſcends.</p>
               <p>Hereby is ſignified a valiant man.</p>
               <p>In the 29. degree, a man tumbling himſelf out of one bed into another.</p>
               <p>A Childiſh man it ſignifies,</p>
               <p>In the 30. degree. A man holding a horſe-ſhooe in his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a black-ſmith.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Of</hi> Capricorne.</head>
               <p>THe firſt face of ♑, is of ♃, and is a face of wandring of travaile, of joy, of gaine and loſſe, with weakneſſe and vileneſs.</p>
               <p>The 2. face is of ♂, and is face of ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch things as cannot be known; and ſeeking aſter ſuch things as cannot be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to.</p>
               <p>The third face is of the ☉, and is a face of covetuouſneſſe, of governing one ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, of not ſufficing himſelf, and of ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting.</p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170163:31"/>
               <p>In the firſt face aſcends a man travailing on foote.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond a man reaching at a bird in the Aire.</p>
               <p>In the thind, a man ſitting at a table tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of mony.</p>
               <p>In the 1. degree of ♑, aſcends two men in like forme.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a jocond amiable perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 2. degree, a man carrying a reed on his ſhoulder.</p>
               <p>In the 3. degree a great Serpent aſcends.</p>
               <p>Hereby is ſignified a wiſe man.</p>
               <p>In the 4. degree, two Rakes in a field.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Clown.</p>
               <p>In the 5. two gates open.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man given to hoſpitality.</p>
               <p>In the 6. degree, a man carrying two dogs on his ſhoulders.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a litigious perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 7. a man ſtanding between two women.</p>
               <p>It denotes a merry perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 8. degree. A hand holding a Bird.</p>
               <p>A fowler it repreſents.</p>
               <p>In the 9. a man falling on the ground.</p>
               <p>It denotes a feeble perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 10. a man with a Lapwing on each hand.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:170163:32"/>
               <p>A Fowler or Hunter, it ſignifies.</p>
               <p>In the 11. degre of ♑, aſcends a King Crowned receiving letters from a meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p>The man hereby ſignified will be an Embaſſador to a Prince.</p>
               <p>In the 12. degree, aſcends a man run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſwiftly.</p>
               <p>It denotes a ſwift perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 13. a man carrying a goates skin on his ſhoulders.</p>
               <p>A hangman it repreſents.</p>
               <p>In the 14. degree, a hand holding a Spear.</p>
               <p>It imports a litigious troubleſome perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 15. a man bending his knees.</p>
               <p>It denotes a noble man.</p>
               <p>In the 16. degree, a man riding an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridled horſe aſcends.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man without power.</p>
               <p>In the 17. degree, a man with a dogs head ariſes.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man full of ſtrife.</p>
               <p>In the 18. degree, aſcends a man divid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in one halfe.</p>
               <p>It denotes a puſillanimous Childiſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
               <p>In the 19. degree, a man having fowr legs ſtanding idle.</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:170163:32"/>
               <p>It ſignifies a man playing or reſting when he ſhould be at work.</p>
               <p>In the 20. degree, an Ape looking on himſelf in a glaſſe.</p>
               <p>It denotes a proud man.</p>
               <p>In the 21. degree, a Maſter holding a book open.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a learned man.</p>
               <p>In the 22. a man digging the ground with a ſpade.</p>
               <p>A labourer it repreſents.</p>
               <p>In the 23. a man leading a woman by the hand.</p>
               <p>A lover it denotes.</p>
               <p>In the 24. a Cooper working on a Caske,</p>
               <p>It ſignifies an artificer.</p>
               <p>In the 25. degree of ♑, aſcends a man with a Hawke on his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Noble man.</p>
               <p>In the 26. degree, a faire Grove of Trees.</p>
               <p>The man ſignified hereby will be a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer in woods.</p>
               <p>In the 27. degree. A man lying on the Graſſe.</p>
               <p>A weake feeble perſon it denotes.</p>
               <p>In the 28. degre, a man carrying earth on his head.</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:170163:33"/>
               <p>It denotes a rich man.</p>
               <p>In the 29. degree, a fairewoman ſitting on a ſtoole.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man full of mirth.</p>
               <p>In the 30. degree of ♑, aſcends the tayle of a fiſh.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man imperfect in his deeds.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Of</hi> Aquarius.</head>
               <p>THe firſt, face of ♒, is of ♀, and is a face of an Anxious Spirit greiving after gaine, and never reſting, of labour, loſſe, poverty and vileneſſe.</p>
               <p>The ſecond face is of ♀, and is a face of beauty, underſtanding, humanity, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty, good manners, complements and freedom.</p>
               <p>The third face is of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, and is a face of detection and affronts.</p>
               <p>In the firſt face aſcends a woman ſitting ſpinning on a Rock.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:170163:33"/>
               <p>In the ſecond a comely perſon well clothed ſitting on a ſtoole.</p>
               <p>In the third a man having an envious look holding his hands on his ſides.</p>
               <p>In the 1. degree of ♒, aſcends a man holding in each hand a bird.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Fowler.</p>
               <p>In the 2. degree, a man holding both his hands upon his head.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a ſorrowfull perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 3. degree. A man holding one hand upon his head.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man full of grief.</p>
               <p>In the 4. a man riding on his treaſure.</p>
               <p>A Merchant it denotes.</p>
               <p>In the 5. degree, a woman going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and a man following her.</p>
               <p>It denotes a ſollicitous perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 6. degree, a man playing with a ſtaſte.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a merry perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 7. A ſword drawn, lying on the ground.</p>
               <p>A Souldier or warlike perſon it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents.</p>
               <p>In the 8. degree, a man holding a chaine in his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man not enjoying him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:170163:34"/>
               <p>In the 9. degree. One man lifting up another from the ground.</p>
               <p>It denotes an idle perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 10. degree. a man ſtanding with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an head.</p>
               <p>It repreſents a man without power.</p>
               <p>In the 11. degree an Armed man with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an head.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Noble man without power</p>
               <p>In the 12. degree of ♒, an armed man ſmiting down a King.</p>
               <p>The man hereby ſignified will be a ruler over a King. <hi>This deſerves a Comment.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 13. degree, a Troop of horſmen Armed.</p>
               <p>I denotes a litigious perſon, and a Robber.</p>
               <p>In the 14. degree. A man holding a boote in his hand.</p>
               <p>It repreſents a ſorrowfull perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 15. degree, two men riding on an Unicorne.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Litigious man.</p>
               <p>In the 16. degree of ♑, aſcends a man holding fire in his hand.</p>
               <p>The man ſignified hereby will be a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer with fire.</p>
               <p>In the 17. deg. A woman lying ſick a bed.</p>
               <p>An infirme &amp; idle perſon it repreſents.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:170163:34"/>
               <p>In the 18: degree. A great Owl ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtill.</p>
               <p>It denotes an envious man.</p>
               <p>In the 19. degree. A man holding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers head in his hand.</p>
               <p>It denotes, a man having power and authority.</p>
               <p>In the 20. deg, a decrepit woman leaning on a ſtaffe.</p>
               <p>A weake feeble perſon it ſignifies.</p>
               <p>In the 21. degree, a man clothed ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on his back on the ground.</p>
               <p>An infirme man it denotes.</p>
               <p>In the 22. degree, a man cutting off a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nothers hands and feet with a hatchet.</p>
               <p>It denotes a wicked doer.</p>
               <p>In the 23. degree, two dogs running together.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man given to ſport.</p>
               <p>In the 24. degree, a man weeping holding his hand on his head.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man alwayes ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p>In the 25. degree, One carrying a great Spear.</p>
               <p>A Theefe and wicked perſon it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies.</p>
               <p>In 26. degree. Water flowing out of a great mountain.</p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:170163:35"/>
               <p>An inſtable unſetled man, it repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents.</p>
               <p>In the 27. degree. A houſe compaſſed about with a hedg.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man ſafe in his deeds.</p>
               <p>In the 28. A man drinking out of a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</p>
               <p>It declares a joyfull man.</p>
               <p>In the 29. degree. A man ſitting on horſe-back, holding a ſword drawn in his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a Warriour.</p>
               <p>In the 30. degree. A King Crowned ſitting.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man living at peace.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:170163:35"/>
               <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Of</hi> Piſces.</head>
               <p>THe firſt face of <hi>Piſces,</hi> is of ♈, and is a face of auxiety, of many thoughts, of journeys, and removing from place to place, of ſeeking after ſubſtance and food.</p>
               <p>The ſecond face of ♓ is of ♃, and is a face of praiſing ones ſelf, of a high minde, of ſeeking after and intermedling with great and high things.</p>
               <p>The third face is of ♂, and is a face of fornication and imbraces of great delight with women and loving peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>In the firſt face aſcendeth a man travail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, carrying a burden on his back.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond, an antient man pointing with his hand to the Skye.</p>
               <p>In the third, a young man imbracing a beautifull woman.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:170163:36"/>
               <p>In the 1. degree of ♓, there aſcends two men with one head joyned together.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a troubleſome and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 2. degree. A man ſitting on the earth.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Clowne.</p>
               <p>In the 3. a man eating a roll of bread.</p>
               <p>The man will be a baker ſignified hereby.</p>
               <p>In the 4. an Unicorne lying on his back.</p>
               <p>A man without power it denotes.</p>
               <p>In the 5. Two Maids ſtanding toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>A merry perſon it fignifies.</p>
               <p>In the 6. A great bird feeding on the ground.</p>
               <p>A covetuous miſer it repreſents.</p>
               <p>In the 7. degree of ♓, ariſes a man hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in each hand a bell.</p>
               <p>It denotes a Sexton or keeper of a Church.</p>
               <p>In the 8. degree. A man ſitting in a tub with a bruſh in his hand.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a maker of bathes.</p>
               <p>In the 9. degree. A Pilgrim walking.</p>
               <p>It denotes a religious man.</p>
               <p>In the 10. A man beating in a morter.</p>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:170163:36"/>
               <p>A laborious man is hereby ſignified.</p>
               <p>In the 11. degree. A man walking with a ſtaffe on his arme.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a vagabond.</p>
               <p>In the 12. degree. A young man look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing behind him.</p>
               <p>Hereby is ſignified a timorous perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 13. degree. A man and woman riding on horſe-back.</p>
               <p>It denotes an idle perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 14. degree. A man cutting wood in a Wood.</p>
               <p>The man will be a labourer.</p>
               <p>In the 15. degree, a man aſcends with a knife drawn.</p>
               <p>It denotes a man preparing himſelf to ſtrife.</p>
               <p>It the 16. degree, a man holding a cock in his hand.</p>
               <p>A Noble man it ſignifies.</p>
               <p>In the 17. degree, a man drowning himſelf in the water.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a ſenſeleſs perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 18. degree two horſmen fighting.</p>
               <p>It Signifies a troubleſome Litigious man.</p>
               <p>In the 19. degree, ♓ aſcends a man piercing himſelf through with a ſword.</p>
               <p>The man hereby Signified will be the cauſe of his own death.</p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:170163:37"/>
               <p>In the 20. degree, a moon ſhining in the night aſcends.</p>
               <p>An inſtable unconſtant perſon is hereby Signified.</p>
               <p>In the 21. degree, two men ſtabbing one another.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies a man-ſlayer.</p>
               <p>In the 22. degree a woman having her girments rent.</p>
               <p>It denotes an immodeſt perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 23. degree, a woman ſwimming in a boat.</p>
               <p>It ſignifies an unconſtant perſon.</p>
               <p>In the 24. degree, a man and woman lying in a bed aſcend.</p>
               <p>A laſcivious perſon it repreſents.</p>
               <p>In the 25. a man caſting a ſtone into a ditch.</p>
               <p>A troubleſome perſon is denoted hereby.</p>
               <p>In the 26. a woman cutting off a mans head with an axe as he lyes aſleep.</p>
               <p>Hereby is ſignified a man ſlayer.</p>
               <p>In the 27. a man ſtanding naked piſſing.</p>
               <p>An immodeſt perſon is hereby repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented.</p>
               <p>In the 28. degree, a man walking by a horſe holding in one hand a bird, and in the other a ſerpent.</p>
               <p>It denotes a man of great underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170163:37"/>
               <p>In the 29. a great fiſh out of the water.</p>
               <p>An unſtable perion it fignifies.</p>
               <p>In the 30. degree, a woman looking in a glaſſe.</p>
               <p>It denotes a proud unchaſt perſon.</p>
               <p>Here followeth the nature and figni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Planets, in the ſignes, and throughout the 12. houſes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> The Signification of <hi>Saturn</hi> in the Signes.</head>
               <p>IF <hi>Saturn</hi> be found to be Lord of a Geniture, and well placed in the Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and increaſing in ſtrength, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſing; he maketh men of a high Spirit; and raiſeth them to great honours; ſeldome laughing, keeping anger long, of good counſell, faithfull, and of approv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good Judgmens, performing all things with Judgment, and reaſon, but not caring for mariage, not affecting wives nor Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. They are alwayes removed and
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170163:38"/>vacant, to themſelves, little eaters, but great drinkers: for the Corporature of their bodies, they are Slender, pale, and wan, an ilfavoured countenance, great ears, and thick lips, thick hard haire, a ſmall heart, a little breaſt, of nature cold, alwayes ſome malignant humour daily offending them, and are very much afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſome inward greife as the colick daily belching and breaking of wind.</p>
               <p>For the moſt part they are malicious, leading a laborious ſolicitous and carefull life, full of daily griefs and imployed about the water or leading their lives in watery places.</p>
               <p>But if ♄ be Lord of the Geniture and in his own houſe, or in his Tearms; or in the houſe of ♃ or in his tearmes; or in the houſe of the ☉: and if the nativity be by day, he maketh the native famous and Noble in his life, giving him much pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and felicity.</p>
               <p>But if he be in the houſe of ♂ or in the termes of ♂, or in the houſe of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, he maketh the native, of a ſorrowfull, labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, humble, ſordid; and inglorious life, and daily afflicted with ſorrow. And theſe evils ſhall be ſtronger, if it be a noct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urnall Geniture; and if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be decreaſing
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:170163:38"/>in light, then the hair of his head is very thin, or he will be much deformed by baldneſs, and ſuch perſons are much ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be ſuddenly taken with blindneſſe, or loſſe of their ſight, through ſome flux of Rehume; he alſo ſignifies pluriſies Dropſies, Gout, Falling-Sickneſſe, Crump, Convulſion-fits, eſpecially if the Lord of the Geniture be afflicted; and ill placed, or impedited by any ill Aſpect of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>. But if he be placed with any benevolent Stars beairng rule and ſtrong, he bringeth thoſe benefits and preferments before ſpoken of: and maketh a good Phyſitian. But if <hi>Aries</hi> be placed with any evil Star, theſe evils he increaſeth with much calamity; he commonly cauſeth long life, and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe through vicious humors. They commonly live in moiſt watery pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, or in ſecret hidden places.</p>
               <p>If ♌ be in the houſe or Tearmes of ☿ he maketh wicked perſons, witches, perjured, haters of their Brethern and parents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170163:39"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIIII. <hi>Of the Signification of</hi> Saturn <hi>in the</hi> 12. <hi>houſes.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SAturn partilely placed in the horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcope in a nativity by day, he that is born then ſhall bee greater then any of his bretheren, or kindred born before him, and ſhall be ſeparated from his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; and by day in all the fourth An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles he alwayes produceth the firſt born, or firſt nouriſhed; or thoſe Bretheren which were born before, do depart out of the place, he giveth a haughty proud and high Spirit. But if ♄ be in the horoſcope by day, and ♂ poſſeſſe any other Angle of the Geniture; or be in the Angle of the Aſcendant, he Signifies much evill and bringeth many Dangers, and loſſe of eſtate and expence of ones patrimony, and more frequently if no benevolent Stars be joyned with them; or caſt their powerfull Rayes unto them.</p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:170163:39"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> in the horoſcope in a naivity by night, he that hath him ſo placed ſhall be troubled with great labours; and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually oppreſ thereby; he ſhall be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in imployments about waters, but his converſation ſhall always be labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> placed in the 2. place from the Horoſcope giveth to the native great ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and many overthrowes; he is a deſtroyer of wife and Children, and a fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent ſtirrer up of great troubles, a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. of the ſubſtance both of Father and Mother, and the native will be ſlow and dull in all his actions; to ſome he giveth continuall infirmneſſe of body.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Saturn</hi> be thus conſtituted and ♂ in any Angle of the geniture, and behold the Sun by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, or ☍. or the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, increaſing with the like Aſpect, he cauſeth poverty and miſery, and a body overpreſt with dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly labours.</p>
               <p>But if ♄, be in the ſecond in a nativity by day, he giveth increaſe of ſubſtance, but ſlowly and by degrees, but the native will be of a low Spirit, and one delighting to live obſcure, and ſecret, and alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying that they have any thing; and he giveth increaſe of eſtate to ſome through imployments about the water.</p>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:170163:40"/>
               <p>♈, poſted in the 3. giveth a ſlow ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh idle body, not regarding to get any e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; but if he be placed in this houſe with the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, or ♀, he maketh the native fooliſh, malicious, ſpeaking ſacrilegious words againſt divinity, waſters of their Patrimony, Theeves; but ſeldom have good ſucceſſe therein.</p>
               <p>If ♈, be thus poſited and ♂, joyned to him by any Aſpect whatſoever; he mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the native a flaſe accuſer, a ſycophant, wicked, malevolent, envious, and maliti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; and alwayes dying an evill death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> partilely placed in the fourth houſe that is in <hi>Imo-Coeli;</hi> if it be by day, he ſignifies the native to be a covetuous hoarder up, and keeper of Gold and Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; but in this place by night, then the native is a ſpender of his Patrimony; bringeth ſudden death to the Father; he alſo afflicteth the body with great ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, cold diſeaſes, and infirme old age.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, behold him by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, or ☍, or if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, be placed in the ſame houſe with him, he giveth barrenneſſe, and cauſeth the native to adopt ſtrangers Children for his own, or maketh him a tutor of little Children, &amp; deformeth the body through
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170163:40"/>ſome hidden griefe wherewith he alwayes languiſheth, he maketh the Mother a wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and afflicteth her with many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes incident to women, and continuall paines and griefs of the ſtomack.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> poſited in the 5. houſe by day, maketh Kings or Dukes, or raiſeth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to great power and authority.</p>
               <p>But if ♈, be thus poſited and not the ☉, but ♃, in the Horoſcope, and ♄, ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated from a 6. of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, he giveth perpetuall felicities, great Power and Magiſtracy.</p>
               <p>But if ♄, be thus poſited and not the ☉, but ♃, in the Horoſcope, he raiſeth the native to a leſſer office of Magiſtracy; but ſignifieth a governour of ſome City or the like; nevertheleſſe he maketh him Lord of a great eſtate, and one that ſuſteineth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by his riches.</p>
               <p>But if neither ☉, nor ♃, be in the Horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcope, and ♄, be placed in the fifth and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated from a ☍, of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, he giveth ſubſtance and poſſeſſions, but commonly the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive leads a ſingle life, or joynes himſelf to ſome unworthy match.</p>
               <p>But if ♄, be thus placed in a Nocturnall Geniture; he giveth ſome happineſſe to the native in the later part of his age, but the continuance thereof is uncertaine and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170163:41"/>the man ſlow in all his actions, but if the moone be joyned unto him, and defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent in light, it deſtroyes a mans eſtate and makes him miſerably ſpend what before he had gotten.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> placed in the ſixt houſe deſtroyes a mans eſtate, for he is alwayes ill poſited there, for he giveth much ſickneſſe, if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, decreaſing be joyned to him, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, or ☍, he is the author of much unhappineſſe, he makes men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy, infamous, vagabonds; ſuch as can ſeldom ſubſiſt long in a place.</p>
               <p>But if ♂, do behold ♄, thus placed by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, or ☍, or be in the ſame ſigne with him, he giveth many hidden and ſecret griefs of body as ptiſicks, dyſenteries; and if they be thus placed and their malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy not mitigated by the benevolent beames of ſome good ſtarre, they bring death to the native by ſome of the fore-mentioned diſeaſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> in the 7. houſe that is the Weſt Angle partilely poſited in a diurnall Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is good, and giveth a good eſtate and old age; ſignifieth the native to be a covetuous keeper of money, and for diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes he ſignifies ſecret infirmities; the Hemorrhoides, and ſhrinking of the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes.</p>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:170163:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> thus placed in a nativity by night cauſeth Fiſtulaes, Hemorrhoides, and ſuch diſeaſes about the fundament, eſpecially if ♂ be in any Aſpect with him, he cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Rheumatick bodies, and the native is very ſubject to impoſtumes, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the death of their wives happen by ſome ſuch infirmity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> in the 8. houſe by day, giveth a good eſtate in old age, and if he be thus placed, in the houſe of ♂, or termes of ♂, he brings profit to the native by the death of ſtrangers.</p>
               <p>But if ♄, be thus placed in a nativity by night, he deſtroys the eſtate of the native; or if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> behold him by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>; or ☍, he is ill placed here; or if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, be in the houſe of ♄, and behold him with the like Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pects; or if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be ſo placed with ♄, and ♂ behold him with any ſuch Aſpect, it brings a violent death to the native; But if ♂, and ♃, behold ♄, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, ſo placed with any good Aſpect, it is fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and giveth a proſperous life, but the native is alwayes unconſtant in his love towards women: a good Aſpect is a a ▵, or ⚹.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn,</hi> in the 9. houſe maketh famous men, opinionated Philoſophers Prieſts, men
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170163:42"/>that have alwayes ſome imaginary opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, alſo according to the quality of the ſigne he maketh witches, diviners, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematitians, interpreters of Divinity, Prelates, ſomtimes Diviners and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of dreames; but moſt frequently he ſignifies, Philoſophers; but ♄, thus poſited in a nativity by night, ſtirreth up the wrath of God, and the hatred of the Prince towards the native eſpecially if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, carry light to him any way whatſoever. but he that is thus borne, receiveth more evil from the anger of God then from his Prince, if ♄ be ſo placed with the Moone and ♂, behold him, but theſe evils are mitigated if ♃ caſt his beames to him from any fortunate place, as if he be in his Termes, Houſe, or Exaltation, or behlods him by a ▵ Aſpect.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn,</hi> partilely placed in the 10. houſe, that is, the mid-heaven maketh Emperors Dukes, Preſidents Magiſtrates, if the Sun be in his exaltation, in the Horoſcope.</p>
               <p>Alſo ♄, thus poſited in a nativity by day, denotes honeſt men, of good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, wealthy Farmers their dwelling and poſſeſſions alwaies adjoyning to the Sea, Rivers or Woods, he giveth alſo great ſubſtance and honour, and poſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſions from great perſons eſpecially, if he
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170163:42"/>be ſo poſited, and in no Aſpect with ♂, but if ♂, be ioyned to him ſo placed he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bateth the good before ſpoken of.</p>
               <p>But ♄, in the mid-heaven in a Noctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Geniture is the author of infelicity, a deſtroyer of ſubſtance, and hindreth mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage and Children, cheifly if he be found in the place ſigne or tearmes of any Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant ſtarre, but if any benevolent ſtarr as ♃, or ♀, behold him with a good Aſpect, they take away his malignity; giving thoſe things which ♄ denyes, being ſo placed by night.</p>
               <p>But ♄, by night is alwayes evill in any of the Angles, and ſignifies much evill to the geniture, for he killeth the wife, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth the Children and afflicteth the whole courſe of a mans life with bitter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils.</p>
               <p>But if ♄, ſo poſited ſeparate from a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, decreaſing, he that hath ♄, ſo placed ſhall alwayes be afflicted with the burden of poverty, ſo that he ſhall ſcarce have daily ſuſtenance to maintaine his life, eſpecially if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, be decreaſing and joyned to him in a feminine ſigne.</p>
               <p>But if ♄, be ſo placed and ſeparate from the beames of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, increaſing, he giveth unſtability and unconſtancy of life, ſo that
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170163:43"/>he that hath ♄, ſo placed, ſhall ſcarce have one courſe of his life like another, but alwayes ſubject to mutability; but ♄ ſo placed, if that ☿ be joyned to him, ſignifies the native to be crafty, ſlye and ſubtill, and giveth long life, eſpecially if he be Lord of the geniture, or giver of life: but if, on the contrary, the Lord of the geniture be oppoſite to the giver of life, it abates 30 yeares of the natives life, and ſignifies grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter evills and more powerfull as often as he is ſo poſited; againſt the Lord of the geniture which the Greeks call <hi>Oicodeſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten:</hi> or if he be placed againſt the giver of life, eſpecially if ♂ behold him by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, or ☍ he giveth the palſy, the native is crooked hunchbackd, ridiculous, deform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed perſons, Hermophrodites, and the like; which things are knowne by the markes and ſubſtance of the corporature of the body.</p>
               <p>But if ♄ be ſo, placed and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſepe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating from him &amp; applying to ♂, in a noc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turnall birth, he ſignifies fools, Luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, melancholy perſons of languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bodies, or ♄, ſo poſited in the laſt quarter of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſing, it ſignifies the ptiſick.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn,</hi> poſited in the 11. ſomtimes ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170163:43"/>good, and ſomtimes increaſes evils: he that is then borne, ſhall live in the ſame place, and after the ſame faſhion as his Father hath done before him, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the 30. yeare of his age he loſeth whatſoever he had gotten, and never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneth to any dignity or eſtate till he hath ſurpaſſed the 30th. yeare of his age.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn,</hi> placed in the 12. houſes ſheweth much ſtrife to the native to happen through words, and dangers, and loſſe by ſervants, and cauſeth bondage, and he giveth to him that hath him ſo placed great griefes, and moderate ſickneſſe, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if ♄ be thus placed, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in any manner joyned to him; But if a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent ſtarre be placed in any Angle of the geniture, then though ♄ be ſo placed he that hath a benevolent ſtar in any Angle of the geniture it doth in ſome ſort mitigate theſe evils and malignancy of ♄, making them more mild and gentle if ♄, be found ſo poſited by day.</p>
               <p>But the evill is more ſtrong and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if ♄, be found thus placed in any nativity by night, but in which of theſe houſes ſoever ♄ is poſited in, diligently inquire out his part, that is, to find out in what part place or tearmes of his Duode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cathemary
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170163:44"/>he is placed; for by the Duode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cathemary and the terms of the Duodeca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themary, you may finde out all the power of <hi>Saturn.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> Of the ſignification of Jupiter in the Signes.</head>
               <p>IF ♃, be Lord of a birth, he maketh men of high Spirits, coveting great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, faith full and alwayes aſpiring to great acts, giving more to themſelves then the faculty of their patrimony or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer requires; Imperious, Noble, Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and honeſt in all their actions, lovers of cleanlineſſe, chearfull and amiable in all their actions, deſiring much meate, lovers and affecters of their freinds, and alwayes delighting in welldoing; a hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome compoſed body, beautifull and faire, faire and beautifull eyes and head, the ſame adorned with thick haire; of a grave gate. Their life is glorious notable, and full of felicity, following whatſoever they
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170163:44"/>deſire, beautified alwayes with a good and honeſt converſation, and protected by the teſtimony of great men, tender over their Wives and Children, their Sons alwayes increaſing their dignity, &amp; bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great honours to their Fathers by their Acts.</p>
               <p>He giveth ſome ſickneſſe or infirmities to the liver through Wind or Crudities, and death by dejection or undue carnall copulation.</p>
               <p>But when ♃ is Lord of a Geniture then looke how ♄ beholds him and the other ſtarres: for what hath beene ſpoken of one, ought to be an example to guide you in the reſt.</p>
               <p>For if ♃, be Lord of ageniture and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the firſt Angles of the geniture in his own houſe, exaltation or rearmes, or in the houſe of the ☉, and in a nativity by day and is adorned with the teſtimonies of benevolent ſtarres, the full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, carrying her light unto him, and ♂ poſſeſſe not any other Angle of the nativity, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, increaſing oppoſe him not, it ſignifies full and compleate feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city.</p>
               <p>But, if he be in any baſe humble ſignes or termes, or in baſe abject places of the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170163:45"/>geniture, and ♃, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, afflicted by any valitious malevolent Planets, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prives him of all power, ſheweth no good ſignification in the geniture, neither doth the native live a full age, for if malevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſtarres do Aſpect him by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, or ☍, according to their ſtrength, they ſhorten his dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> The ſignification of Jupiter in the <hi>12.</hi> Houſes.</head>
               <p>IUpiter partily placed in the 1. Angle that is in the Horoſcope in thoſe ſignes in which he rejoyneth, or in either of his own houſe Tearmes or exaltation, he mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the native noble glorious, cheife ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler to Cities, ſometimes ſignifying the cheife governour of great Cityes, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the meaſure of his ſtrength in the geniture, by nature he ſignifies good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nevolent honeſt chearfull and rich perſons eſpecially if he be placed in the Horoſcope by day, and aſpected by no malevolent
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170163:45"/>ſtarre. For if ♃, be ſo placed and male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent ſtarres behold him with ill Aſpects it greatly diminiſhes the good ſignified by <hi>Jupiter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ♃, be placed in the Horoſcope in a nativity by night he ſignifies the native to be the firſt borne, or the death of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren that were borne before him, or ſeperates him farre from them, ſignifies him to be the governour of ſome Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try or chiefe ruler in his Fathers houſe; to be delicately brought up &amp; his parents to live in great felicity.</p>
               <p>But if ♃, poſſeſſe this place by night and malevolent ſtarres behold him, he ſignifies the native to be a ſpend thriſt and a deſtroyer of the eſtate of his Father and Mother. But alwayes ♃, placed in any Angle of the geniture, either the native is the firſt borne or his brethren dy that were borne before him, and he beares cheife Rule in his Fathers houſe, but of he be in the Horoſcope whether it be by night or by day, if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſing be joyned to him by any Aſpect whatſoever, he ſignifies great Magiſtrates, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Citties, or men imployed in weighty affaires.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in the 2. houſe ſignifies poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170163:46"/>in forraign Countryes, and from ſtrangers, he giveth great dominions and poſſeſſions to Noble men, if he be ſo plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, &amp; ☿ joyned to him by any good Aſpect.</p>
               <p>But ♃ ſo placed, if ☿ be joyned to him and ♂ or ♄ behold them, it ſignifies mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tability of eſtate, changing from good actions to bad; and he that hath ♄, ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited, all the tearme of his life will be vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and ſubject to mutability, ſometimes abounding with riches, and other times caſt downe under the burden of poverty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in the 3. houſe is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther good nor evill, but equally moderate; ſomtimes a helper forward to ſpend an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate; and ſomtimes a gatherer together of riches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in the 4. houſe that is in the <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum Coeli,</hi> ſignifies Lawyers, Judges; men loving Cattle, Hredſmen, Tillers of the ground, according to the nature of the ſigne, Embaſſadors of Kings or Dukes; or ſuch as to whom is given the charge of ſome publique government in a Common-Wealth; meſſengers often ſent to and fro, by the command of the King, Prince or Judges: he frequently ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to be employed in ſome publique actions by the King, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Religious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170163:46"/>Pilgrims, fortellers of things to come; reverend Churchmen, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Some, according to the quality of the ſigne are finders out and diſcoverers of hid treaſure; but alwayes ♃, being ſo placed, giveth to the native a happy old age to the time of his death.</p>
               <p>But if ♃ be ſo placed, and the ☉ in ☍, to him he ſignifieth the Father to be noble and honorable; but the native will ſpend his eſtate in his middle age, and get it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine afterwards, he will be ſlow in Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nereous acts, diſaeffcted to Children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter,</hi> thus placed by night, gives an indifferent eſtate, and in proceſſe of time happineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in the 5. houſe, ſignifies great felicity, and the native to be honored with ſome publique preferment, eſpecially if he be in his houſes, or in his termes, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, or in the houſe of the ☉. But if ♃ be thus placed, and ♂ behold him with any good Aſpect, he ſignifies Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and ſuch as have the power of life and death, but if without ♂, <hi>Mercury</hi> and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be joyned to him, he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies Officers pertaining to Kings; if ♀, alone be joyned to him, he giveth perfect happineſſe; if ♉ be joyned to him
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170163:47"/>he giveth length of yeares and old age, and giveth Children of both ſexes, eſpecially if he be Lord of the geniture, or Lord of part of the Horoſcope, or Lord of that ſigne wherein the Lord of the geniture is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
               <p>But if in a nocturnall geniture he be placed oppoſite to the giver of life (for ♃, rejoyceth not in nocturnall genitures) he diminiſheth 12. yeares of the natives age; but if in a nocturnall geniture, ♂, ♀, or the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be oppoſite to him, they fill the native with many vices according to the nature and quallty of the ſignes: in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſignes they are libidinous exceſſive luſtfull and prepoſterouſly effeminate, in 4. footed ſignes, Hunters, Lovers of Wild-beaſts; frequent haunters of Woods and deſert places; and given to much la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour: in earthly ſignes, herbariſts; deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to know more of the ſecrets of nature then is lawfull: in watry ſignes, fiſhers or ſuch as get their living about Rivers the Sea or watry places, truly laborious and alwayes living thereby.</p>
               <p>But if ♃, be thus poſited by night, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing theſe ſtars, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperating from him, he ſignifies an unconſtant life, ſubject to much unhappineſſe, but the
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170163:47"/>ſame is in ſome ſort mirigated, if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate from him and apply her ſelfe by a good Aſpect to ♀: but if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, depart from him and go to ♂, with any ſtarre, it ſignifies much miſery and unhappineſſe.</p>
               <p>But if ♃, be thus placed and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from him, and apply to ♂, by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, it denotes a violent death to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive according to the nature and quality of the ſignes; for if ♂ behold the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, with and ☍, ſo departed from ♃, in a nativity by night, it ſignifies wranglings, dangers, and ſtrife with inferiour people.</p>
               <p>Wherefore <hi>Iupieer,</hi> in this ſigne by night commonly ſignifies calamities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in the 6. houſe ſignifies much e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, if he be lord of the ſigne wherein the Horoſcope is or of the mid-Heaven, or behold the ☉, ♄, or ♂, by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, or if he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, decreaſing by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>; or the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, be decreaſing in the ſame ſigne: but if he be not afflicted by any evill ſtarre, and receive the light of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, increaſing the evill is thereby mitigated, he ſignifies here ſouth-ſayers, embroyderers in Gold, Silver-Smithes, but nevertheleſſe, if they gaine any thing by theſe artes, they quickly ſpend it.</p>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:170163:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in the 7. houſe ſignifies wealth and long life in a nativity by day, but in nocturnall genitures, he generally ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies Wives and Children; for the native ſhall loſe a deare Wife, and ſee the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable death of a Son or a Daughter. But in old age he giveth increaſe of eſtate, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe but meane, and ſo much as he ſhall not want.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in the 8. houſe, commonly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyes ones eſtate, raiſeth up a great many enemies, ſtirreth up ſeditions commonly among the people and malicious acts; he ſignifies the native to be ignoble, a proud fooliſh boaſter; full of prepoſterous ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity, and mad raging folly; eſpecially if there be an evill ſtarre in any Angle of the geniture, but if he have ☿ with him, or in ▵, to him or the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him with any good Aſpect, he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies procurators or meſſengers of Kings; and the native alwayes to die in his youth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter,</hi> in the 9. houſe by day ſignifies Prophets and Foretellers of things to come, interpreters of the Oracles of God, Preiſts, Churchmen, and ſomtimes he ſignifies loſſe or damage; in a nativity by night he ſignifies, dreamers of falſe dreames and the like.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:170163:48"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in the 10. Houſe or mid-Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſignifies Princes, publique officers, Chiefe Governours, men alwayes graced with publique honors, and deſirous of praiſe, but luxurious of life; men em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed about the affaires of Kings or great men; to ſome he giveth happineſs through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their whole lives, but commonly he ſignifies felicity, if no evill ſtarre hinder; but if any malevolent ſtarre hinder him whatſoever eſtate honour or dignity is got in Youth, he looſes and conſumes in Age, unleſſe the 7. houſe be fortified with ſome benevolent ſtarre.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in the 10. Houſe by night ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies honeſt men, and of good manners, but apt eaſily to be deceived, and ſudden waſters of their eſtates.</p>
               <p>If ♃, be in the 11. houſe in a nativity by day he gives much happineſſe, great riches power and government, if the ☉, and ♀, be joyned to him by good Aſpect, but if it be in a nativity by night and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in ☍ to him, the good is thereby aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but if ♂, be in the 8. contrary to him, though the native have great riches ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and dignity, he turneth it all to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and unhappineſſe.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:170163:49"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iupiter,</hi> in the 12. Houſe giveth good fortune, ſignifies the native to be power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful over his enemies and a terror to them; eſpecially if a malevolent ſtarre be in the aſcendant or ♂, in the 7. houſe; but ♂ in the 7. undoubtedly ſignifies a ſudden vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent death, and the evills and calamities of the native will be more prevalent and greater if the ☉, and ♄, behold ♃, by an ☍; but if in a nocturnall geniture the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſing oppoſe him, it ſignifies great poverty. But if neither ☉, nor ♄, be in ☍ to him &amp; are in good houſes, nor the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> afflict him; theſe who have ♃ ſo poſited, may thrive, by ſome art or myſtery, as Gold-ſmiths or embroyderers of garments with Gold, painters or workers of Silver, but what art ſoever it be, it will be ſought after and praiſed, if ♃ be ſo placed and ♀ joyned with him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:170163:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> The ſignification of Mars in the ſignes.</head>
               <p>IF ♂ be Lord of a nativity he ſignifies, men of proud Spirits, ſubject to no reaſon, immoveable, contentious, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacious, head-ſtrong, fearing no danger, ſubject to be deceived, great eaters, vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant, high-minded, ignorant, having red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haire, eyes bloud-ſhotten, imperious, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes deſiring to rule over others, of a prepoſterous mind, not careing for Wife, Children nor freinds, greedily coveting o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens goods; he ſignifies hurt by fire, and Iron, as cuttings or burnings, falls from high places, or burſtings in the lower parts of the body, he giveth a ſudden or violent death; if he ſeperate from the full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, death by theeves, or condemned by the Magiſtrate for ſome offence, but if his malice be kindled by the beames of the ☉, it ſignifies openly deſtruction by burning. But ♂, is more ſtrong if he be
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170163:50"/>Lord of a birth by day, and be in any An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle, and the full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in any other Angle afflicted by the beames of <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, or giving her power to ♂. But if in a nativity by night he be in the houſe of ♄, or ♃, or in their tearmes, or in his own houſe or tearmes, or in the 5.11.10. or firſt, and behold the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſing, or the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſing give po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werto ♂, or ♃ joyned to him in an Angle by a ▵ he ſignifies Dukes, Captaines, Tyrants, terrible rulers, men of great power, but if be in the 7th. houſe in ♂, as before ſpoken, he denotes the native ſurely to dye a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent death: for alwayes ♂, in the 7th. houſe ſignifies a violent death; but the kind there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is to be judged according to the nature and quality of the ſigne,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:170163:50"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> The ſignification of Mars in the <hi>12.</hi> Houſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArs,</hi> partilely placed in the aſcendant by night in a maſculine ſigne, maketh Souldiers; By day, without the beames of ♃, he ſignifies bountifull men willing to give more then their eſtates will beare, ſomthing profuſe, but their acts all bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanced with reaſon.</p>
               <p>But if by day the aſcendant be the houſe of ♂ and a maſculine ſigne, and ♂ therein; and ♃ with him, or beholding him with a good Aſpect, he ſignifies generalls and cheife Captaines of Armies, Lords of life and death, and terrible to all Cities, or Countryes they approach unto, happy va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant and grave, greatly ſubject to anger, not greatly affecting Wife nor Children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in the aſcendant by day ſignifies crafty audacious furious perſons, vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, inſtable, never finiſhing any thing with reaſon, full of revenge, ſpenders of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:170163:51"/>their eſtate, looſing all the ſubſtance of their lives, and Wives, and Children not reſerving any patrimony for them, and dye young: but if ♃ be in his houſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation or tearmes, and behold him with a <g ref="char:trine">△</g>, he mitigates theſe evills every way. But I know and have found in many geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, when ♂ hath been in the aſcendant, the natives to have beene baniſhed, and have beene good Governours in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> in the 2. Houſe is very unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate by day if it be in the morning, he maketh the native to wander from his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe and home, and wander up and down in ſtrange Countries, but if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, increaſing be with him or in ☍, or <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, to him he ſignifies ſlow feeble perſons, ſubject to receive hurt by Iron, Colds, or fower-footed-beaſts, ſomtimes he maketh Seamen, men ſubject to be Captives or come in bondage through their own wit, but high-minded in their greateſt neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
               <p>But if ♃, he joyned to him by good Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect or in his houſe or tearmes, he bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the native out of danger, freeth them from Captivity or impriſonment, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtores them to liberty. But ſomtimes they
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170163:51"/>are in want: but ♂, ſo placed by night, ſignifies the native to be a knight or a great ruler, but ſuch as ſomtimes ſhall be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to dangers, though aſſiſted by the beames of ♃, or ♀.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 3. houſe ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſhall attaine to honour with great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, covetuous of other mens goods, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying all men, and having a wicked con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but if <hi>Iupiter,</hi> be in the 11. or 7. he ſignifies the native may attaine to an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate through great labour in ſome pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Office; if <hi>Iupiter</hi> be in ♂ with him, he giveth great riches and power exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing others in nobility, or if he be in the 3. in his own houſe termes or exaltation, and <hi>Iupiter</hi> joyned to him, he ſignifies Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates and Governours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 4th, houſe by night ſignifies common Souldiers, ſuch as live in deſert Countryes, keepers of wild beaſts, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times waſters or ſpoilers of Countryes, according to the quality of the ſigne, it deſtroyes both life and eſtate of the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, giveth widdow-hood, ruine, one Child or none, and he that hath one ſhall be hindred by him in all his actions; by day he ſignifies weake, feeble, lame bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, ſubject to receive hurt by Iron, op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170163:52"/>by women, alwayes ingratefull, but if the ☉, behold him by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, or ☍, or be in ♂ with him, theſe evills he augmenteth and maketh the native mad or lun atick, if the aſcendant be the houſe of ♂.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 5. houſe by night in his own houſe or in the houſe of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> or in his tearmes or exaltation, or if <hi>Iupiter</hi> be with him, or behold him in his own houſe by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g>, ſignifies much honour, a great eſtate, much honour and love amongſt great men.</p>
               <p>But if ♂, and ♃, be thus poſited and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> apply to ♂, by a fortunate Aſpect, it ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies great honour &amp; power to the native, Captaines and Generalls of Armeis, to whom is commited authority over life and death, and great power of the ſword; but if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> behold him not, but Venus be with him or behold him by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g>, he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the native to be rich and happy, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing honourable acts; of proper hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome bodies.</p>
               <p>But by day, <hi>Mars</hi> ſignifies the native ſhall ſpend his eſtate, and frequently change his houſe; and becauſe of misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes happening to him, he often dies in a ſtrange Country, or undergoes ſome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent danger.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:170163:52"/>
               <p>But if ♃ or ♀ be joyned to him or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> or ⚹, they bring great profit to the native by travaile, and recall him ſoone home to his own Country. But if by day the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſing be in ☍ to him, let him feare great trouble, or danger of bondage to happen to him: For although he ſeeme to be happy, yet his happineſſe is alwayes ſubject to the power of another; for he ſignifies Councellors to great Judges; accuſations, ſeditions, troubles, loſſe and ſudden dangers; weakneſs in ſome part of the body, ſomtimes madneſſe, burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing feavers, which cauſe phrenſies; he alſo ſignifies Jayles, Bondage and impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, unleſſe <hi>Jupiter</hi> beholding the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the ☍ to ♂, or ♂ himſelf abate theſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities; for <hi>Jupiter</hi> brings ſudden help, ♂ alſo in this place by day denies Children without the teſtimony of <hi>Jupiter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 6th. houſe ſignifies much ill, brings hurt to Children, gives inequali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of life, he gives diſeaſes according to the quality of the ſignes, in crooked ſignes he denotes lamenſes and crooked deformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and ſignifies all kinds of diſeaſes in this place.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 7th. houſe is very evill, cauſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth great dangers to the native, ſignifies
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170163:53"/>great labours, homicides, wicked perſons, guilty, Inventors of wickedneſſe, Tormen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Hang-men, Traytors. But if he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold his own houſe by an ☍, he gives not a violent death for ♂, never deſtroyes his own houſe; but generally ♂, in the 7. by day or night cauſes a violent death, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the nature of the ſigne; But theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills are more violent in ſignes contrary to him for in this Place he gives many griefes and troubles of body, ſomtimes ſudden death or perpetuall impriſonment; in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivities by night he cauſeth trouble to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed from all their actions oftentimes cauſes wounds by fire or Iron, great ſecret diſeaſes and infirmities of body, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly if he be lord of the time, or partake thereof with the full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>. But if ♄ be poſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Mars,</hi> or in the mid-heaven, or it be the power of ♄ or if the full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> apply to ♂ or ♄, it denotes great evill to the native, and many misfortunes; ſomtimes accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſomtimes impriſonment, ſomtimes loſſe, great ſentences pronounced againſt him, or he is caſt unto wild-beaſts; caſt down headlong, deſtroyed by domeſtick treachery, killed by theeves, or periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth by ſhipwrack, but theſe are diſcerned by the quality of the ſignes; for in earthly
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170163:53"/>ſignes he ſignifies death by wild-beaſts, in ſolid ſignes, deſtruction by ſome fall head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long, in watry ſignes drowning, in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane ſignes to periſh by the ſword: but if the ☉ be in ☍, to him or with him or in any Angle of the geniture, he ſignifies the native to be burned alive, and afflicts him with lamentable miſeries; before the laſt day of his life, he ſhall ſuffer hurt by fire, iron, violence, torments or homicides, ♂, alſo greviouſly afflicts Wives and Children in the 7th. houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> in the 8th. houſe, by day, either denies any eſtate, or cauſeth the native miſerably to ſpend what he hath; if he have the ☉ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in ☍ he cauſeth blindneſſe but if he be alone in this place he ſignifies want penury trouble ſedition and danger, but if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in the ſecond, and ♃, in no Aſpect to <hi>Mars</hi> and behold not the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, he giveth a violent death, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the quality of the ſigne, in humane ſignes to be ſlaine by the ſword, by Pirates or theeves, or by his own houſhould, or to be put to death for ſonne crime by the ſentence of the Judge; and to come to ſome publique cruell death, without the teſtimony of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> or ♀ in earthly ſignes to be ſlayne in ſome deſert place having
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170163:54"/>firſt undergone great troubles in four-foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſignes to be drowned in ſome River or Lake, or caſt into the Sea by Pirates: in ſolid ſignes, death by a ſudden fall; in fie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſignes, burning.</p>
               <p>By night, he ſignifies the native to be crafty, and have ſome good office, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe violent or ſudden death.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Jupiter,</hi> be joyned to him or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him by any good Aſpect, he mitigates theſe evills, or if ♃ be in the aſcendant or the aſcendant the houſe of <hi>Iupiter</hi> or ♀, theſe mitigate and abate his malice.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 9th. houſe is good, giveth a happy and honourable life, eſpecially if <hi>Jupiter</hi> be in the aſcendant; but by night, if <hi>Jupiter</hi> be in the Horoſcope, he ſignifies Magiſtracy; ſuch as have the power of the ſword, leaders of Armies, but frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cauſeth ſome dammage in travailes; but if the 9. be the houſe of ☿ or ♀, he ſignifies learned famous Doctors and Orators; but if he be in his own houſe, or in the houſe of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> or in his exaltation, and <hi>Jupiter</hi> not in the aſcen dant, it ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to be a terr or to evill Spirits, and ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily to expell them, and command them to depart out of any one, that is poſſeſt with them.</p>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:170163:54"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 10th. houſe, by night in his own houſe or the houſe of <hi>Jupiter</hi> in a maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culine ſigne, or in his exaltation, ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the native to great danger, and often is eaſie to be deceived, nevertheleſſe he ſignifies cheife rulers, Captaines, Lords of life and death, Tyrants and terrible Governours in Townes and Countries, but commonly dying an evill death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 11th, houſe, is very fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate and good, giveth increaſe of eſtate, and lore amongſt people, giveth ſome dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity or preferment, if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be with him decreaſing, and <hi>Jupiter</hi> be old him with a good Aſpect, or be with him or joyned to him by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g>, then he ſignifies Judges or ſuch as have the power of the ſword.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in the 12th. houſe by day, giveth great troubles and evill, ſignifies loſſe by wicked treacherous ſervants, much ſickneſs cares and dangers; but by night, theſe are all mitigated. We ought alwayes to wiſh in all genitures either by day or night that ♂ be in ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood Aſpect, either with ♀ or <hi>Jupiter,</hi> for they abate his malice; and alſo it is to be deſired that <hi>Mars</hi> poſſeſſe no Angle of any birth, for <hi>Mars,</hi> in any Angle of a geniture by day doth divers wayes afflict the native, if by day <hi>Mars</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170163:55"/>poſſeſſe one Angle, ♄ another, and ♃ ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he ſignifies a violent death to the natives or to be ſelfe murderers.</p>
               <p>But if by day ♂ be in one Angle, and ♀ in another, he wearies the native with daily evills; either they are killers of their Wives or themſelves; if ♂ poſſeſſe one Angle by day, and ☿ another, he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies fooles and void of reaſon, if by day ♂ poſſeſſe one Angle, and the ☉ another, loſſe and death by fire, if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, violent death, and the mother to dye a cruell death; if he be by day in any Angle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> or ♂ of any other ſtarre, he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies great ſickneſſe and debility, ♂ like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe by day in any Angle or lord of the houſe of Children denies Children: if he be the giver of life by night he gives long life, if in a diurnall geniture he be the giver of life, he kills the native in his youth, but if another Plannet be giver of life, and ♂, behold him by an ☍ or <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, he diminiſheth 15. yeares of the natives life, if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> interpoſe between him and ♄ he cauſeth lameneſſe or weakneſſe to ſome part of the body according to the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification of the ſigne; if he behold the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſing by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, it ſoone kills the native.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:170163:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> The Suns ſignification in the ſignes.</head>
               <p>IF the ☉ be lord of a geniture and well placed, he ſignifies faithfull perſons, but proud, wiſe, doing all things with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, ful of humanity, religious, honourers and lovers of their parents, he ſignifies perſons of corpulent bodies, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low haire: he denotes husbandmen ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt perſons gaining an eſtate by vertuous actions, but diſaffected to Wives and Children; of diſeaſes, he ſignifies infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities about the eyes and other parts of the body frequently happening by fire, and publique or violent death in ſtrange places the ☉ increaſeth the time of life if he be well placed and not impedited by the beame of any malevolent ſtarre.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170163:56"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XK.</hi> The ſignification of the Sun in the <hi>12.</hi> Houſes.</head>
               <p>THe ☉ in the Horoſcope hardly gives any brethren, but in a maſculine ſigne or in his own houſe or exaltation or joyned to the benevolent Aſpect of ſome good Plannet, ſheweth great nobility; but if he be joyned to malevolent ſtarres it blemiſheth the eye-ſight, but if ☉ be in the aſcendant by day, he ſignifies Kings and great rulers; but if his power be hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, Counſellors. But becauſe we have ſaid he giveth great felicity in the firſt houſe, it ought to be explained, for if ♄ be poſited with him by day it ſignifies Kings and Emperours; if ♂ Aſpect the ☉ or be placed with him it ſignifies great en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, danger and trouble to the native to keepe his power: but the ☉ in the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, and ♃ in any other Angle, and ♂ in the 10, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in any other Angle, it denotes great power and dignity to the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170163:56"/>native; but if the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Jupiter</hi> be ſo poſited, and ♂ in the 10. or 7. and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> with <hi>Mars</hi> in the 10. or 8, it ſignifies the native, be he King or Emperour, to dye a violent death, or to be impriſoned and depoſed from his honour according to the nature of the ſignes.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Saturu</hi> be in the 10. he ſignifies potent perſons the ☉ in the aſcendant, and ♃; ♀ and ☿ in the other Angles ſignifies great men of happy perſons, proſperous and abounding in riches, and alwayes free from the burden of Poverty; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if <hi>Saturn</hi> behold the ☉ with a <g ref="char:trine">△</g>, or ⚹. But if the <hi>Sun, Jupiter</hi> ♀ ☿ and ♄ be thus &amp; poſited ♂ behold them with a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, or otherwiſe be evill placed or joyned to them, he ſignifies great potent perſons having power of life &amp; death, but Theeves Robbers, Tyrants, greedy after other mens eſtates, and at laſt to be baniſhed or ſuffer a violent death.</p>
               <p>The ☉ in the aſcendant in a nativity by night ſignifies the native to be a more baſe ſordid perſon, but, if ♄ or ♂ be with the <hi>Sun</hi> or behold him by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍ it ſignifies the native will kill his elder brethren, and deſtroy all his own eſtate and ſubſtance and the <hi>Sun</hi> in any Angle of a geniture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitateth
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170163:57"/>the elder brethren; unleſſe the native be the firſt borne.</p>
               <p>The Sun in the 2. houſe ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to be carefull in ſeeking an eſtate; and in all their lives good and affable of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition; but languiſhing in their bodyes, and of a ſhort life, and croſſed with many troubles: but if ♀ and ♃ behold the ☉, with any good Aſpect as a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> or ⚹ or be with him; they bring ſome unexpected good to the native, and increaſe of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, raiſing up men that are dejected and caſt down, to ſome publique office or dignity.</p>
               <p>The ☉ in the 3. houſe ſignifies an evill death to the Father, ſignifies the native to be invalid and of no repute, but if ♃ and ☿ be joyned to him by good Aſpect, he ſignifies grave Counſellors, Treaſurers, Rulers and Governours of Cityes and the like, but if he be in the 3. in his own houſe or exaltation, or in the houſe or exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ♃ ♀ or ☿, he ſignifies devout religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, but if ♄ or ♂ be with him, or joyned to him in other ſignes, he ſignifies perjured perfidious perſons, prophane ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious wicked blaſphemers.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Sun</hi> in the 4. houſe Aſpected by ♄, or <hi>Mars</hi> ſignifies the death of the Father,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170163:57"/>deſtruction of the whole family and eſtate, nevertheleſſe he ſignifies a happy old age, but the native unconſtant in his affection towards his Wife and Children.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol,</hi> in the 5. houſe ſignifies amiable &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable perſons eaſily attaining all things they deſire, and beloved of all their friends but if he be ſo placed with ♀, or ſhe behold him with any good Aſpect <g ref="char:trine">△</g> or ⚹, he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies great honour and dignity to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</p>
               <p>But although malevolent ſtarres be with him or in Aſpect to him, it doth not much hurt the native, becauſe of the naturall goodneſſe of the place, but is only hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to the Children of the native.</p>
               <p>The ☉ in the ſixt houſe is hurtfull to the native and giveth great and long ſickneſſe and if ♂ be in the aſcendant, he afflicts the native, with hurt, or ſome wound by Iron; denotes the Father to dye a ſudden evill death, and deſtroyes the natives eſtate. But if any good ſtarre be in the 10. he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies riches great poſſeſſions, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive happily to enjoy his Fathers eſtate. But although there be no ſtarre in the Medium <hi>Coeli,</hi> if <hi>Jupiter</hi> and ♀ be with the ☉ in the 6. houſe, they mollifye and miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate all evill.</p>
               <pb n="96" facs="tcp:170163:58"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> in the 7. houſe is very ill, and gives many infirmities and diſeaſes, eſpecially if ♂ and ♄ behold him with any Aſpect, or be placed with him; he brings much ſickneſs and affliction to the native, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the malignancy of the afflicting Planner.</p>
               <p>But if the ☉ be in the 7, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> with him, or in the 10. or aſcendant, he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies potent and noble perſons, men in great authority; chiefly if he be in his own houſe or exaltation, or in the houſe of ♃, and have part of fortune in any Angle.</p>
               <p>The ☉, in the 8. gives ſudden death to the Father, if ♂, or ♄ be with him or Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect him by <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, he ſignifies dotage, fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling evill, Phrenſies and vicious diſeaſes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the nature of the ſigne.</p>
               <p>But if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in ☍ to him and the ♂ or ♄ do Aſpect him by <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, he ſignifies diſeaſes of the head, Lunatick, Ptiſick and Dropſies, according to the nature of the ſigne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sol.</hi> in the 9. houſe, ſignifies builders of Churches and religious perſons, lovers of Divine Worſhip, makers of hymnes and Divine Songs, and gaining glory thereby; and ſignifies the Father to be of a happy eſtate, and to lead a happy life; but
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170163:58"/>nevertheleſſe many changes and mutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of life to happen to the native.</p>
               <p>The ☉ in the 10. houſe, in a diurnall ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture in his own houſe, or the houſe of ♃, or in his exaltation; ſignifies potent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, men in great offices, power and dignity; but if ♂ be in the 7. houſe and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in any other Angle beholding ♂, let the native be King, Duke, or of what degree ſoever; he ſignifies that he ſhall ſuffer im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment. But generally the ☉ in any Angle with ☿, ſignifies learned and devout perſons, Orators and ſtudious of various kinds of learning and curious Arts, the ſame effects ☿ produces, if he be farre from the ☉, free from ♄ and ♂ and ♃ and ☿ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him by any good Aſpect.</p>
               <p>The ☉ in the 11. houſe ſignifies noble perſons, men of a good happy eſtate and condition; living in great credit, and in proceſſe of time increaſe of felicity, and the greater if ♃ or ♀ be with him, or behold him by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> or ⚹ Aſpect: neither do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>levolent ſtarres impedite or hinder the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, but only are obſtructive to the place of Children.</p>
               <p>The ☉ in the 12. houſe frequently ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies ignoble perſons ſervants and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, ſudden death to the Father, and
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170163:59"/>deſtruction of the eſtate, and great afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and diſeaſes to the body: if good ſtarres be with him nevertheleſſe he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies ignoble perſons, but if malevolent ſtarres, be with him; he giveth perpetuall-calamities of body and continuall bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage and ſervitude.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXI.</hi> The ſignification of Venus in the ſignes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VEnus</hi> being Lady of a nativity, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies loving amiable cheerefull perſons luxurious, gratefull, honeſt, near, libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous; godly, juſt ſincere and faithful freinds of uncorrupted freindſhip, of a ſlender handſome body, pleaſant countenance faire eyes, thick haire, a little curling, a beautifull corporature, great drinkers, but little eaters, covetuous of venereous acts; oft entangled in love; honeſt and virtuous in all their actions; lovers of mirth, delighting in muſick, makers of muſicall inſtruments, Painters, if ♀ be placed in the Principall places of the geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170163:59"/>ture, ſhe ſignifies great fame and honour to the native, ſtudents in ſacred learning. the men great affecters of women, and the women of men, that are thereby ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified; ſhe ſignifies the native to be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and to have many Children, and their Children to be great joy and comfort to them.</p>
               <p>But the poſiture and dignity of this ſtarre is diligently to bee noted: for in a nativity by night, if ſhee bee in the firſt 5.10. or 11. or in her own houſe exaltation or Tearmes, or receive power from the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſing or be beheld by ♃, by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> or the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> apply to her without the teſtimony of ♄, ſhe ſignifies Councellors, Treaſurers, and honourable perſons, or if <hi>Mars</hi> do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her with a <g ref="char:trine">△</g>, ſhe alſo giveth great power and dignity, if ♂ be in his own houſe or in the houſe of ♃, or in his tearmes, or in the tearmes of <hi>Jupiter,</hi> or in his exaltation, and Venus; be free from the beames of the ☉. But if ♀ be thus placed with ☿, or in his houſe, tearmes, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation; or ☿ in the houſe of ♀, or in her tearmes, and in good houſes or places of the geniture, he ſignifies ſundry changes and varieties of life. But if ♀ be ill poſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, in the houſe or tearmes of ♄ by night
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170163:60"/>or ♂ by day, ſhe ſignifies unchaſt luſtfull perſons, afflicted with daily calamities and miſchances, receiving great diſgrace by luxurious luſt and unlawfull love; and ſuch as bring to themſelves publique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy and diſgrace by reaſon of adultery and unlawfull luſts; and for this cauſe to dye a ſhamefull violent death, eſpecially if ♀ be in the 7. and behold <hi>Mars</hi> with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ill Aſpect.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXII.</hi> The ſignification of Venus in the <hi>12</hi> ſigne.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VEnus</hi> in the aſcendant in a nativity ſignifies Divines, godly men, belov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of great men, imployed in their affaires good Orators according to the nature and quality of the ſigne; in humane ſignes ſhe ſignifies Preiſts, Preachers, foretellers of things of come; ſhe denotes courteous honeſt men and rich, if ſhe be not impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited by ſome malevolent ſtarre: if ☿ be with her, it ſignifies good muſitians; in
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170163:60"/>ſixed ſignes, and ſignes of a ſmall voyce ſhe ſignifies great ſtudents, lovers of their Princes; in earthly or watry ſignes, em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broyderers or Painters; in four-footed ſignes, noble Heroick Spirits, lovers of Cattle, and a nativity by day ſhe ſignifies infamous libidinous unchaſt perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus,</hi> in the 2. houſe ſignifies inventers of Curious arts in a nativity by night, but often branded with infamy, but by little and little attaining to a happy condition; gratefull, and free in love <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> in this place by day ſhe giveth many croſſes, hinders marriage, and giveth ſudden death to the wife: but if ☉ or ♄ behold her with a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍ or be with her, ſhe cauſeth barrenneſs and inſufficiency in Venereous acts; the native never marries but is a great lover of Children.</p>
               <p>But this influence is more potent, if by day ♀ be in the houſe of ♄ ♂ or ☿ or in their tearmes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> in the 3. houſe is fortunate if well Aſpected by ♃, the native is religious and marries one belonging to the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> poſited in the 4. houſe deſtroyes an eſtate, and cauſes Widdow-hood, the native is alwayes uncapable of getting any thing, and if ſhe be joyned with ☿, ſhe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies Adulterers.</p>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:170163:61"/>
               <p>But by night in this place ſhe raiſeth in proceſſe of time to credit and honour and ſignifies the native to bebeloved of great men, and to live in good favour and credit, ſhe ſignifies the firſt part of youth to want nothing, but nevertheleſſe the mind to be filled with ſome vices, acor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the quality and ſignification of the ſignes. For in tropick or double ſignes ſhe ſignifies Widdow-hood and loſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout women; in ſixed ſignes, love and an eſtate by women, ſetting ♒ aſide for ♀ in the 4. in this ſigne with the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> or in <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, to her, cauſed barrennes; and ſuch as care not for marriage.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> in the 5th. houſe is fortunate and ſignifies good honeſt perſons, ſuch as ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fily attaine to their deſires; if ♃ Aſpect her, ſhe ſignifies famous men and ſuch as attaine to great dignity if ♀ be placed with her, he augments the promotion and preferment of the native, but brings Infamy and dilgrace therewith.</p>
               <p>But ſhe ſignifieth the native to be a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querer in all things, and to receive rewards of victories; foretellers of things to come, great gainers by wives or women.</p>
               <p>If ♀ be poſited in the ſixth houſe, whether it be by day or night, ſhe ſignifies ignoble Wives, Widdowes, or weak women, if no ſtar be in the mid-heaven.</p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:170163:61"/>
               <p>if a woman have ♀ poſited in the ſixth houſe of her nativity, it ſignifies ſhe ſhall have hard difficult labour, and undergoe great perill in Child-birth; but a benevo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſtarre in the 10. cauſeth happineſſe and good fortune.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> poſited in the 7th. houſe, in her own ſigne by night, gives a happy old age; but hinders marriage and Children, but brings ſome diſgrace to the native by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of venereous acts, and if ♂ be with her or joyned to her by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, ſhe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies unchaſt laſcivious libidinous perſons and if ♂ and ♀ be ſo poſited, and ♄ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them by <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, or be poſited with ♀ it denotes that women that have ♀ ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited to be unchaſt and lſacivious; and theſe vices are the more potent, if theſe ſtarres be conjoyned with ♂ in ♑.</p>
               <p>If ♀ be in the 8th, houſe, ſhe hinders marriage, and ſignifies the Wife to be barren and deformed, if the native do mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; but if ☍ be with her, and malevolent ſtarres behold them, by <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍ or be with them it ſignifies deſtruction of your native eſtate; and death by a Gonorthea or Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexie.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Venus</hi> in this houſe by night ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies riches to the native, and great profit
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170163:62"/>by the death of women, and denotes a ſudden death, but without terror or tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> in the 9th. houſe by day ſignifies the native to be much tempted of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, to goe ſordidly without dreſſing his haire, pretending themſelves to be Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, and interpreters of dreames, and the more if <hi>Saturn</hi> be in any Aſpect with <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a nativity by night ♀ ſignifies religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, devout worſhippers of God, ſtudious of ſacred and religious things; and ſomtimes the natives to be imployed in ſome office about the Church, or in Kings houſes, or about making Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for women, whereby they increaſe their eſtate.</p>
               <p>But if ♂ behold ♀ ſo poſited by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍ eſpecially if he be angular, he gives to the native many enemies; and his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to ſuffer cruell death, and that for adultery or whoredome.</p>
               <p>But if ♀ be ſo poſited, and ♃ or ☍ behold her with a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ♄ by an ☍, and ☍ in <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> to him, or ♄ and ♀ with ☍ thus placed ſhe gives barrenneſſe, ſignifies lovers of Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, luſtfull perſons, and by reaſon of ſuch vices given to homicide and ſuch Crimes.</p>
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:170163:62"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> in the 10th. houſe, ſignifies hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py men; famous and of great and happy fortunes; if ☍ be with her, Muſitians, ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, artiſts; if ♄ and ♂ be not joyned to her by any Aſpect, ſhe ſignifies Muſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and Philoſophers, but if ♄ behold her with any Aſpect, if ſignifies infamy, and men of no power nor repute, but ſuch as commit the tuition of their eſtate to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; if it be a woman that hath ☍, ſo poſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, it ſignifies her to be unchaſt, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe her ſelfe to every luſt, full of whoriſh actions, and to proſtitute her ſelfe to whoreing to maintaine her life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> in the 11th. houſe by night Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by ♂, and ♄, cauſeth barrenneſſe; and hinders marriage: but by degrees in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth an eſtate, by the helpe of friends; nevertheleſſe ſhe ſignifies honeſt perſons, and if ſhe receive the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be ♂, ſhe ſignifies wealth and power to the native ſomtiems the cheife ruler of a City.</p>
               <p>But if by day ſhe be thus placed with the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, it ſignifies power wealth and good fortune to the native, from his youth to the day of his death, and the rather if ☍ be with them, or Aſpect them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> posited in the 12th. houſe by night ſignifies dally trouble and griefe to
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170163:63"/>a woman, by reaſon of luſt and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full love; if the native be a man ſhe ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies him to marry his maide, or ſome common whore, whereby he is without Children, but ♀ in this place by day ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies death to the native, through wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, according to the nature of the ſignes for this ſtarr hath various inſtuences which are difficult to be found out; for as a Pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter by mixture of ſeverall colours brings them to the true form and colour of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect body, ſo the Aſpects of the ſtarres and intermixture, one among another alters and changes their natures.</p>
               <p>For if ♀ be thus poſited, and ♄ joyned to her, if ſignifies men of perverſe mindes full of vices, and neceſſary for no act, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecoally if it be in a nativity by night; but if ♃ behold them with any Aſpect, he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates this malice, and conferres much good to the native, increaſe of his eſtate and free from vice.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in ☍ to ♀, it ſignifies infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous luſtfull perſons, lovers of Children, given to inceſt whoredome and coveting unlawful beds; or if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be wth ♀ in ☍, or behold her by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, it alwayes ſignifies the native to burne with unlawfull luſt, if it be a woman, ſhe is mch given to luſt, promiſcuous love and pleaſures.</p>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:170163:63"/>
               <p>But in a nativity by night ♀ poſired in a good ſigne and well Aſpected by ♂, gives increaſe of happineſſe wealth and honour. But by day, if ♂ behold her with any Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, it ſignifies much ill fortune, for ♀ re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceth by night if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>. ♂ or ☍ be joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to her, and gives much happineſſe and felicity to the native.</p>
               <p>But if ♀ be in this place with the ☉ ſhe ſignifies injuſtice, for ſhe is ill placed here with the ☉; but ſhe rejoyceth here in the morning behind the ☉, and ſignifies good with the good, and increaſe of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</p>
               <p>But if ſhe be Lady of the aſcendant and of the geniture, and placed in a good ſigne ſhe giveth long life, but if the giver of life oppoſe the Lord of the aſcendant in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, by day, it abates 8. yeares of the age, and affects the native with ſome vices; but ſuch as do not much ſtaine him with infamy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:170163:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> The ſignification of Mercury in the ſignes.</head>
               <p>IF ☿ be Lord of the geniture, he ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies witty ingenuous perſons, eaſily learning all things, modeſt ſearchers into the ſecrets of all arts, covetuous of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; if he be in his own houſe tearmes or exaltation, or in the houſe of <hi>Venus,</hi> or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold her by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g>, he maketh poets, elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Orators; in the houſe of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> he ſignifies men of a gracefull ſpeech.</p>
               <p>But if ☿ be in the houſe or tearmes of ♄ and ♃ or ♀ behold him with a good Aſpect, or if ♃ be in any Angle, or in the third houſe, he ſignifies the native to be addicted to religion, ſearchers into ſecret magical arts, Mathematicians, Aſtrologers, Religious, faithfully keeping the bond of friendſhip, juſt and honeſt, doing all things with reaſon and counſell.</p>
               <p>But if <hi>Mars</hi> behold him by any Aſpect or apply to him by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, and if ☿ be in the
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:170163:64"/>3th. houſe in humane ſignes adorned with the teſtimony of ♃, or ♃ in the firſt or 10. he ſignifies advocates, Orators, men of great wit and ingenuity, attaining their deſires by their own power.</p>
               <p>But if ♄ be in ☌ with him in a noctur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall geniture, and placed in the beſt places of the geniture, he denotes treachery accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations and ſtirs up the people with envy.</p>
               <p>But if ♄ do ſo behold ☿, and ♂ be in the 7th. houſe, and he receive the light of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſing, it ſignifies the native to be put to death for ſome evill deed, ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, or falſe money, or the like.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> being lord of the geniture ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a ſmall handſome body, pale faced faire beautifull eyes; moderate eaters and drinkers, ſtudious of all kind of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and by reaſon of their eloquence of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten imployed in ſome embaſſy, loving ſecret learning; he ſignifies maſters of Grammer or Oratory, Phyſitians or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters, carefull in all their buſineſſe, and thereby gaining an eſtate, free from luſt and luxury, walking ſtrictly from the vulger converſation; but if he poſſeſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny houſe of ſickneſſe or vice, or the threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning raies of malevolent ſtarres; it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies vicious humours, if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be ill placed
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170163:65"/>either lunatick, the Cramp or Lameneſſe and death thereby, of by the water.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXIIII.</hi> The ſignification of Mercury in the <hi>12.</hi> Houſes.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MErcury</hi> in the aſcendant in a diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall geniture in ſuch ſignes wherein he rejoces ſignifies Philoſophers, Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marians and Geometricians, and ſuch as ſtudy celeſtiall ſciences, and are apt here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, skillfull in ſaered learning, good orators, advocates; eſpecially if he be in his own ſigne.</p>
               <p>But if ☉ ♄ or ♃ behold ☿ in a nativity by day, it ſignifies great men, crowned with religious actions, and oftentimes imployed in the affaires of their Prince.</p>
               <p>If ♂ behold ☿ ſo poſited by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, or with him in the aſcendant, he caſts down the native through multiplicity of evills; but if ♂ behold ☿ with a <g ref="char:trine">△</g>, he ſignifies proſperous actions to the native.
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170163:65"/>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> placed in the aſcendant by night ſignifies Divines; and men eaſily attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to whatſoever they ſeeke after, he alſo ſignifies the native to be grave and honeſt according to the nature of the ſigne, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the interpreter to a Prince or cheife ruler.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> in the 2. houſe in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſignifies men ſecretly and obſcurely wicked; without learning; and deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of any helpe to maintaine a lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood.</p>
               <p>By night or in the evening he ſignifies worſhipfull perſons, men imployed about other mens eſtates. But by day the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive is alwayes afflicted with miſery and trouble.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> poſited in the 3. houſe, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies Preiſts, Architectors, Mathematiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Inventors of new arts, eaſily apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves to learne any art, if ♃, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold ☿ by <g ref="char:trine">△</g> or ⚹, he ſignifies men of a great wit and underſtanding, good Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, and if ♂, Aſpect him ſo poſited with ♃, he gives great honour and power to the native.</p>
               <p>In the 4. houſe ☿ ſignifies men of an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute wit, and good learning, and if it be in the morning, Maſters of ſecret Arts.</p>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:170163:66"/>
               <p>But if ♂ and ♄ poſſeſſe any other Angle of the geniture, it ſignifies accuſers, keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Jayles, and frequent loſſe, but in a nocturnall geniture, he ſignifies workers of Gold, or diggers in mines of Gold, maſters of all ſecret arts: Captains and Governours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> in the 5. houſe ſignifies hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Gold and treaſure, providently getting an eſtate, keepers of other mens treaſure and goods; he alſo in this houſe ſignifies the native to have many Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>But by night he ſignifies profuſe ſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of their eſtate, or that they are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted with; and ſuch as ſeldome keep a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny money, he ſomtimes alſo ſignifies Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ometritians, and Aſtrologers.</p>
               <p>Somtimes ☿ placed in this houſe, in ☌, with the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſing, afflicts the body with many diſeaſes and infirmities.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> in the 6th. houſe, brings great fortune to the native, and highly advances him, by reaſon of his faculty in learning, eſpecially if another Planet, be in the 10th. houſe.</p>
               <p>By night in this houſe, he ſignifies inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, fiſhers, fowlers, ingravers, if there be any other ſtarre in the 10th. houſe.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170163:66"/>if he be orientall in a nocturnall geniture and no other ſtarre in the 10th. he ſignifies malignant malicious perſons, authors of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Counſels, theeves, lyars, having a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy covertuous deſire, after other mens goods, bearing a bitter hatred to their freinds and neighbours, full of evill acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> in the 7th. houſe in a diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall geniture, ſignifies the native to be full of vice and wickedneſſe; burning with wicked and unlawfull luſts; ſignifies wives to be whores, according to the nature of the ſigne; if he be in the houſes of ♂ or ♄ he ſignifies Whores, Bauds, and ſuch as are ſordidly wicked,</p>
               <p>In the 7th. houſe by night <hi>Mercury</hi> ſignifies rich Wives, and profit by women, Muſitians, Notaries, Schoole-maſters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> in the 8th. houſe Occidentall in a nativity by day, ſignifies ſluggiſh per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; not willing, nor daring to do any things, fooles, malicious, and good for nothing; but if he be in the houſe or tearmes of ♄ he maketh the native deafe eſpecially if ♄ behold him with any Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, but by night in this place, he ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the native to have ſome eſtate from ſtrangers, and to be finders of ſome hidden treaſure.</p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:170163:67"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> poſited in the 9th. houſe not Aſpected by any other ſtarre ſignifies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious perſons, profeſſinng themſelves to know much but maſters of nothing, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litious and acting nothing by reaſon.</p>
               <p>But if he be in this place orientall, he ſignifies Preiſts, Divines; South-ſayers, Aſtrologers, Mathematitians, Phyſitians and ſuch as get their livings by ſuch arts, and if any benevolent ſtarre Aſpect him, he gives them good ſucceſſe &amp; great happineſs.</p>
               <p>But if malevolent ſtarres behold him or be in <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍ to him, he ſignifies irreligious ſacrilegious perſons, ſpoilers of Churches vagabonds, exiles.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> in the 10th. houſe, gives to the native ſucceſſe in great and admirable actions, grave, wiſe, and benevolent, faithfull, and imployed for Princes, and great men if ♃ behold him by a <g ref="char:trine">△</g> or ⚹, and it be a nativity by day, or if ♀ behold him with the like ctſpect, by night.</p>
               <p>But if ♂ behold ☿ by either <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, he divers wayes hinders promotion by ſome kind of offence, and hereupon cauſe often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times baniſhment, or ſome great dammage and loſſe; and if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be joyned to ♂, it cauſes a violent death.</p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:170163:67"/>
               <p>If ♄ behold ☿ by <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, it ſignifies the imployment of the native to be alwaies in watry places, either the Sea, or ſome Pond or River, and alſo cauſes diſeaſes through the abounding of vitious hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> poſited in the 11. houſe ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies ingenious perſons, qualified, fit for all manner of actions, and to be intruſted in great offices, if ♃ be in good Aſpect to him.</p>
               <p>In the 12th. houſe ☿ alſo ſignifies inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious perſons, intruſted in great affaires; but ſomtimes they are in danger, whether the event will be proſperous or not.</p>
               <p>But becauſe ☿ is good with the good, and bad with the bad, we will explaine his ſignification with every Planet in a geniture, for by day if he be well placed with the ☉ and ♃, he is very fortunate; if with ♂, unfortunate, and cauſes much hurt to the native. But by night he alters his nature, for with ♀ and <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, he is good; but with the ☉ very evill and unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:170163:68"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXV. <hi>Of the</hi> Conjunction <hi>of</hi> Mercury <hi>with</hi> Sol.</head>
               <p>MErcury with the ☉ by day in the aſcendant, ſignifies Kings, Dukes, and great perſons. But by night, ſignifies the Father to be ignoble; they will alſo be good Artiſts, but live private and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, according to the nature and qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the ſignes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and the <hi>Sol</hi> in the 2d, houſe gives increaſe of eſtate; and imployment about Princes.</p>
               <p>The ☉ and ☿ in the 3d. houſe in ☌, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy interpreters of dreames, Phyſitians, Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, South-ſayers, Inchanters, Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Mathematitians, Fortune-tellers.</p>
               <p>In the 4th. houſe ☿ and the ☉ in ☌ ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies ignoble perſons; skillfull and ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in hidden and unlawfull arts, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe honeſt and grave: but the ſigne is deligently to be conſidered, which they are poſited in, and the Lord of that ſigne;
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170163:68"/>for it is dangerous if they be ſo placed in the houſe of ♄.</p>
               <p>the <hi>Sun</hi> and ☿ in ☌ in the 5th. houſe, ſignifies noble perſons, eaſily bringing to perfection, all things they deſire; but it is dangerous, they never having con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant felicity; and apt to deceive many.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and the ☉, in ☌ in the 6th. houſe, ſignifies poore, ſluggiſh, but labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious perſons, of ignorant parents dull and ſlow in all their actions, unleſſe ſome other ſtarre be in the 10: but if any other ſtarre be in the 10th. houſe, it is a ſigne of riches, ingenuity and honour, eſpecially if a benevolent ſtarre be in the 10th. houſe.</p>
               <p>The ☉ and ☿ in ☌ in the 7th, houſe, by day ſignifies great power &amp; riches to the native but nevertheleſſe a violent death.</p>
               <p>But by night in this place they are very evil ſignifying perpetual evil to the native, and to ſeeke his nouriſhment by daily la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and alwayes to be imployed in ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did actions, and of ſtinking arts &amp; trades.</p>
               <p>In the 8th. houſe ☿ and the ☉ in ☌, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies ſeeble diſeaſed perſons, eaſy to be deceived; in this place they ſignify ſudden death, and frequently madneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and the ☉ in the 9th. houſe ſignify exorciſts, and ſuch as cure perſons,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:170163:69"/>Poſſeſſed with details and evill Spirits, and by ſuch arts gaine the greateſt part of their living.</p>
               <p>The ☉ and ☿ in ☌ in the 10. houſe in ſuch ſignes as they rejoyce in or are exahed in, ſignifie great potent and powerfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons eſpecially if they have the reſtimony of ♃.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and the ☉ in ☌, in the 11th. houſe, in the latter part of ones age give increaſe of eſtate and felicity.</p>
               <p>The ☉ and <hi>Mercury</hi> in <hi>Conjunction,</hi> in the 12th. houſe, denotes poore unhappy perſons, ſervile flaves and ſuch as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes dye in a wandring Condition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:170163:69"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXVI. <hi>Of the</hi> Conjunction, <hi>of</hi> Mercury <hi>and</hi> Saturn.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MErcury,</hi> and ♄ in ☌ in the aſcendant in a diurnall genitute ſignifies hiders of money, advocates, men well skilled in the law, ſcribes, but of languiſhing bodyes and ſoone dye.</p>
               <p>By night in this place they ſignify ſlaves ſervants and Captives; and of freemen to be delivered into ſervitude and bondage to potent men.</p>
               <p>If they be in a feminine ſigne, in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity by night; they ſignifie Evnuchs or barren men; impotent in copulation, ſordid, filthy, impudent, immodeſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>In the 2d. houſe ☿ and ♄ by day ſignifies herbariſts and Phyſitians, rich and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous in all their actions, ſomtimes Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors according to the nature of the ſigne.</p>
               <pb n="122" facs="tcp:170163:70"/>
               <p>By night in this place they ſignifie lyars fools, madmen, keepers of Churches, weake in ſome part of their bodyes and full of ſundry vices, often ſubject to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed and put in priſon having no Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ♄ in the 3th. houſe ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies water-bearers, makers of Ornaments for Funeralls keepers of dead bodys or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers, Porters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn,</hi> and ☿ in the 4th. houſe ſignifies ſtudents in ſecret and unlawfull arts, and get their living thereby; but ſome that have ♄ and ☿ in the 4th. are oftentimes ſubject to impriſonment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> and <hi>Mercury</hi> in ☌ in the 5th houſe cauſe the natives oftentimes to change their houſes and dwellings, ſignifie keepers of Granaries, of Gemmes, Pearls, Aromaticks and mettalls, and revealers of holy things.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn,</hi> and ☿ in ☌ in her 6th, and 12. houſes ſignifie in both alike, for by day in either of theſe places they ſignifie know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg inmany ſiences, ſeeking into ſecret arts and myſteries, deſirous to know all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane things, they are malitious and envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; and often afflicted with vitious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</p>
               <pb n="123" facs="tcp:170163:70"/>
               <p>But in either of theſe houſes by night they ſignifie authors of falſe letters, mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious, wicked malefactors, alwayes, full of miſcheife, but if ♄ and ☿ be in either of theſe houſes by day or night, and ♂ Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect them either by <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, unleſſe the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill be avoyded, he ſignifies men to be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by death for ſome Criminall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ♄ in ☌ in the 7th, houſe ſignifies heires of women, covetuous of great eſtates, and lovers of women.</p>
               <p>If they be in this houſe, by night they denote miſery to the native, all his life and involved in many debts, vitious and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of body, malignant and malitious, and ſubject to impriſonment, for ſome accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion laid againſt them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ♄ in the 8th. houſe in proceſſe of time, give increaſe of life and ſubſtance, and to ſome, an eſtate by the death of other men, but they ſhall be trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with ſome diſeaſes about the belly; by night in this place they ſignifie poverty and languiſhing ſickneſſe, if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing apply to <hi>Saturn,</hi> or the full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> to <hi>Mars.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the 9th, houſe, ☿ and ♄ ſignifie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, makers of ſuperſticious Images and religious ceremonies.</p>
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:170163:71"/>
               <p>In the 10th. houſe <hi>Mercury,</hi> and <hi>Saturn</hi> ſignifie the native to inherit the eſtate of ſtrangers, inventors of great things, wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, actors, or ſomtimes the procura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of great men; if a fortunate ſtarre Aſpect them, they ſignifie men of a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine wit, Orators, Maſters of Oratory or Grammarians, or Maſters thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ♄ in ♂ in the 11th. houſe fignifie the ſame things as they doe in the 5th.</p>
               <p>In the 12th. houſe, ☿ and ♄ have the ſame ſignification as in the 6th. houſe is expreſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:170163:71"/>
               <head>CHP. XXVII. <hi>Of the</hi> Conjunction <hi>of</hi> Mercury <hi>aud</hi> Jupiter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MErcury,</hi> in conjunction with ♃ in the 1. houſe ſignifies noble men, virtuous honeſt and honourable, cheife magiſtrates or Governours of Townes and Citties, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes delighting in Juſtice and honeſt actions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ♃ in the 2. houſe in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity by day ſignifies the native to have poſſeſſions and an eſtate adopted to him from ſtrangers, and in proceſſe of time great felicity, but in this place by night they ſignifie fooliſh perſons; of no durable felicity, much ſubject to be deceived.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♃ in the 3. houſe ſignifie Magitians, but alwayes lovers of good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and virtue makers of hymnes, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons perſons and exciters of others to reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious exerciſes, keepers of temples, fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellers of things to come, all which are alſo ſignified by theſe Planets in the 9th. houſe.</p>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:170163:72"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Merury,</hi> and ♃ in ♂ in the 4th. ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies ſingers and Organiſts, Curates, Tutors of Children and ſuch as have the tuition of women, and ſomtimes to finde ſome hidden treaſures by chance, whereby they attaine to great happineſſe.</p>
               <p>In the 5th, houſe, ☿ and ♃ by day or night do ſignifie the ſame thing: in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of time they raiſe the native to great power, and make them happy in all their actions, eaſily attaining what they deſire, the ſame ſignification they have in the 11th. houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ♃ in the 6th. houſe by night and day have the ſame ſignification, and are very fortunate, fignifying happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the native in all his actions, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if any other ſtarre be in the 10th. houſe, or if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> apply to them, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes great riches to the native, and to flow in money, to be Lords of much Gold and great poſſeſſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ♃ in the 7th. houſe by night or day, ſignifies gaine and profit from wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, publique offices, men of long life a happy old age of good Counſell and good manners, alwayes coveting good things, but if it be in a nativity by night and ♂ behold ☿ and ♃ by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍ it di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſheth their goodneſs.</p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:170163:72"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ♃; in ♂ in the 8th. houſe in a diurnall geniture are but moderatly good; the native ſubſiſting by his own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention, they ſignifie ſome diſgrace to the native: in his youth, but in the latter part of his age increaſe of eſtate.</p>
               <p>If they be in this houſe by night, either the native gaines ſomthing himſelf to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt well on, or ſome great eſtate is confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon him, but they denote a ſickly body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ♃ in the 9th. houſe have the ſame ſignification as in the third.</p>
               <p>In the 10th. houſe ☿ and ♃ ſignifies magiſtrates and men or great power ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quality of the native.</p>
               <p>In the 11th. houſe they have the ſame ſignification as in the 5th.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury,</hi> and ♃ in the 12th. houſe in a nativity by night and orientall, ſignifies ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries to Princes States or great men, Notaries; but often offending, ſubject to much unhappineſſe in their youth, or put to a violent death, but in a diurnall ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture, they ſignifie the native not to be ſo much ſubject to offences; and to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue longer in their place or office; if in this place they be Occidentall, the native is more ſlow in his actions, they denote a ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170163:73"/>unhappy fate, much ſubject to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and popular actions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXVIII. <hi>Of the</hi> Conjunction <hi>of</hi> Mercury <hi>and</hi> Mars.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MErcury</hi> and ♂ in ♂ in the firſt houſe, are very unfortunate, and Signifie unhappineſſe, to befall the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive by unlawfull love; and for ſome evil deed, to be put to a violent death, if it be a diurnall Geniture. But by night he Signifies men of great Offices, Captaines, and ſuch as ſhall have good ſucceſſe in warr.</p>
               <p>But if by night ♂ ☿ be ſo poſited and ♄ behould them by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍ he Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies much unhappineſs to the native, ☿ and ♂ in the 2. houſe, by day Signifies vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, fugitives, Captives, and a violent death, if the full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> behold them, but in this houſe by night, Signifies men of an evil minde; wicked, malicious, but ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to be deceived in all their Actions.</p>
               <pb n="129" facs="tcp:170163:73"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♂ in the 3d. houſe, Signi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies foretellers of things to come, ſuchas are much converſant in Implovment about Churches and in proceſs of time, happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>☿ and ♂ in the 4th. houſe, ſignifie men of a poor unfortunate Condition, enemies and treacherous to their parents and freinds, practiſers of unlawfull acts, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes by their evil actions involving themſelves into trouble; bringing pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty upon themſelves, and ſubject to great and long ſickneſſe, if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> behold them by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ♂.</p>
               <p>But if it be by night, they Signifie the native to come to ſome publique office, as Captaines or Magiſtrates, but to dye a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> and ☿ in the 5th. houſe, Signifies valiant noble men, Conquerers, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible in all their actions, publique treaſurers; tyrants and terrible to all their adverſaries.</p>
               <p>In the ſixth houſe, ☿ ♂ in a diurnall Geniture, ſignifies great ſickneſs, Impriſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the native to ſuffer much by falſe accuſations, and Circumventions of his Servants and ſervile perſons, or to ſuffer falſe Impriſonment for others mens facts;
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170163:74"/>and to ſuffer great torments, or a violent death, eſpecially if the full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> any way beheld them.</p>
               <p>But if ♂ and ☿ be thus poſited by night, they ſignifie the native to be much in debt, or ſuffer much by uſury; they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note ſluggiſh and dull perſons in all their actions; and to ſuffer many unjuſt accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, by their ſervants and envious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</p>
               <p>Sometimes the natives are cruell to their ſervants, afflicting them with over much labour, hunger, and torments.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♂, in the 7th. houſe, in a diurnall Geniture, Signifie the native will kill his wife or ſome other woman by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſome unlawfull luſt, and by reaſon thereof to ſuffer Impriſonment and death; but generally ♂ and ☿ ſo poſited ſignifies Homicides, Theeves, Pirates, and ſuch like according to the nature of the ſignes, alwayes purſuing evil actions and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a publique ſentence of death; for ſome wicked fact. If they be thus poſited by night they Signifie the native to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved in trouble by reaſon of ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull acts committed with women.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♂ in the 8th. houſe, in a diurnall Geniture, ſignifie the native ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170163:74"/>attaines to what he deſires, ſubject to many dangers, and loſſe of all their eſtates; fooliſh and willfull perſons; often Impriſoned, and dying a violent death.</p>
               <p>By night in this houſe, he ſignifies men of evil parts; ſtudious to execute evil of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, and alwayes living by evil acts: it ſignifies Theeves, Robbers, Faith-Break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Inventors or Actors of wickedneſs, Tormentors, Hangmen, ſubſiſting by ſuch actions, or oftentimes ſubject to dy a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent death.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♂ in the 9th. houſe, Sig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies irreligious unjuſt perjured perſons; of erronious mindes, ſpoilers of Churches, ſacrilegious, eſpecially if they be farr from the Sunbeames, or oppſiote to the Sun, or in his houſe, or if the fulls <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> behold them by <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♂, in the 10th. houſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies weak and miſerable perſons, loving navigation, and watery places; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſlaves to Kings and great Men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the quality of the ſignes.</p>
               <p>But commonly ♂ and ☿, in the 10th houſe, ſignifie the native to be imployed in ſome publique office, but not long to continue in it, by reaſon of ſome falſe accuſation,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170163:75"/>to be againſt him, whereby he will loſe his place and eſtate: unleſſe he be friendly aſpected by <hi>Jupiter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♂ and ♀ in the 11th. houſe, ſignifie alwayes the native to dye in fight; lovers of watery places, of weapons, ſound Counſellers; happy in all their actions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♂, in the 12th. houſe, are very unfortunate, and ſignifies many Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamities to the native, for they who have ♂ and ☿ ſo poſited, are much addicted to falſe-hood and wicked acts, much oppreſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with debt; ſubject to ſuffer publique ſhame and diſgrace, by reaſon of their perfidious wickedneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb n="133" facs="tcp:170163:75"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXIX. <hi>Of the</hi> Conjunction <hi>of</hi> Mercury <hi>and</hi> Venus.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MErcury</hi> and ♀ in the aſcendant in a diurnall Geniture, ſignifies men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to the guards of Princes treaſures, or ſuch like Offices: they alſo ſignifie Muſitians, Dancers, making of Muſicall In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſttuments; publique Magiſtrates, Orators, Grammarians, Arithmeticians; by night in the aſcendant, they repreſent men of acute wits, ingenious in all their actions, Prieſts makers of Images, and; in time, to attain to great Dignity; Embaſſadours of Princes, of a gracefull ſpeech and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♀ in the 2d. houſe, in a nativity by day, ſignifie men imployed in noble actions, and long to perſevere therein, grate full and courteous in all their lives, but ſubject to luſtfull vices.</p>
               <p>If they be orientall in this place, they ſignifie the natives to gaine an eſtate
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170163:76"/>by their own induſtry, happy learned men, practiſing, learning, and muſick, cherefull honeſt, gracefull perſons: In a nocturnall Geniture, if they they be occidentall in this place they foreſhew great happineſſe, and an increaſe of eſtate.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♀, in the 3th. houſe ſignifie good diſputants in Religion, Prieſts, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, ſuch as have ſome great office or authority in the Church, Embaſſadors of Princes.</p>
               <p>In the 4th. houſe ☿ and ♀, ſignifie the native to be skilfull in occult learning, Magitians Philoſophers, alwayes ſtudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing celeſtiall ſciences, profitable to all men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> &amp; ♀, in the 5th. houſe, give great riches in proceſs of time. And great gifts or profit from women or wives, and love amongſt great perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♀ in the 6th. houſe, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie an eſtate by learning, eſpecially if ſome good ſtar be in the 10th. houſe, but they ſeldome marry, but are luſtfull and receive ſome diſgrace thereby.</p>
               <p>In a nocturnall Geniture, if they be orientall in this houſe, it ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to marry ſome ſervile ſervant, wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, or harlot, and always to be ſervile
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170163:76"/>and laborious, and imployed about the the water, if there be no ſtarr in the 10th. houſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♀, partilely placed in the 7th. houſe, ſignifie many hidden and occult diſeaſes, in the liver, Phrenſies, Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly, and the like, alwayes diſaffect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to Marriage, and in famous all their lives.</p>
               <p>But by night in this houſe, they ſignifie the native to gain much riches, and an eſtate by wives and women; to obtain to much honour and dignity in their old age: if neither ♂ or ♄ aſpect them but eſpecially ♄; for if ♂ or ♄ behold them by any aſpect, they turn all the good we ſpeak of, to the Contrary.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> and ♀, in the 8th. houſe, ſignifie in a diurnall Geniture, if they be occiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall the native to be gelded, alwayes to be imployed in laborious actions, vitious in body &amp; minde, not marrying, for they will be barren and unfit for generation, and dye either vexed with evil Spirits, of an apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexy or Phrenſie.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercruy</hi> and ♀ in the 9th. houſe, fignifies the native to gain his living by ſome Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment or office belonging to Churches, Prieſts, Aſtrologers, fortune-tellers, Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:170163:77"/>
               <p>In the 10th. houſe ☿ and ♀ poſited, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes the native to gaine honour from the people by ſome publique imployment, but to receive ſome diſgrace by reaſon of ſome actions of their wives.</p>
               <p>But if they be orientall in this place, they ſignifie inventers of Muſick; play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of publique comedies; but unhappy in marriage, for they either marry Whores, or publique infamous wives; or they will be given to many vitious luſtfull plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</p>
               <p>In the 11th. houſe ☿ and ♀ ſignifies per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, exerciſed in imployments about wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; truſted with the eſtates of women; and thereby raiſing their own fortunes; but afterwards are againe dejected and caſt down by contrary fortunes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> &amp; ♀ in the 12th. houſe by day, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie lovers labouring with the vice of luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full love, &amp; are perſpicuous and notoriouſly known to all to abound in thoſe vices, &amp; thereby toſuffer great loſſe; and to come to a violent death, through luſtfull vices.</p>
               <p>But in this place by night, ☿ and ♀ ſignifie the native to ſuffer much affliction by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of whores or unworthy women, and ſubject often to be deceived in their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and of their eſtates.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb n="137" facs="tcp:170163:77"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXX.</hi> The ſignification of the <hi>Moon,</hi> in the ſignes.</head>
               <p>IF the <hi>Moon</hi> be Lady of a geniture &amp; well placed, ſhe ſignifies men ſtable, conſtant, honourable, honeſt, of a large faire body, eating much meat, caring for little drink; but the courſe of their lives unequall and ſubject to change and variety, that ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times their eſtate doth increaſe daily, and is againe ſuddenly caſt down and dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; they delight to live or be conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant about watry places; well affected to their Wives, Children, Fathers and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
               <p>But if any malevolent ſtarres caſt their beames to the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, they give to the native ſome infirmity about the eyes, either disfiguring them with ſome wound or hurt thereabouts, or elſe obſcureth the ſight with ſome miſt or cloud before it: it alſo deformeth the beauty of the body with many ſcarres or marks, as leproſie, or ſome malignant wounds; debilitates the whole
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170163:78"/>body. But theſe things the teſtimony of good ſtarres prevents.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XXXI.</hi> Of the Moon in the <hi>12.</hi> houſes.</head>
               <p>THe <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the aſcendant in a nocturnall geniture at full, and in thoſe ſignes wherein ſhe rejoyceth, gives great increaſe of fortune, raiſeth the native above his brethren, and to great deſerts in age.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in this houſe by day ſignifies, Admirals or cheife Governours of Ships; but if by day the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in the firſt, and ♂ or ♄ poſſeſſe any other Angle of the geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; if they behold her by <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, or be with her, it ſignifies cruell Pyrates, but if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be ſo poſited with evill Planets and Aſpected of no good Planets, it ſignifies a ſhort time of life to the native.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 2d. houſe in a nativity by day ſignifies men of famous and perſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions, but luxurious and much given to voluptuous delights, their imployments to be in ſundry places, and to live in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to others.</p>
               <pb n="139" facs="tcp:170163:78"/>
               <p>If <hi>Saturn</hi> be in the aſcendant and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in this place diminiſhed in light, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies blindneſſe to the native by reaſon of ſome ſudden hurt or wound in the eyes; if ♂ be in the aſcendant it ſignifies Ruptures, Hemerhoids, and ſuch like infirmities.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 3d. houſe ſignifies the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be ignoble, ſpotted with ſome kind of infamy; but if ♃ be poſited with her, it ſignifies the native to gaine by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome publique Treaſurer: but if ♃ and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be ſo poſited and ☿ behold them, it ſignifies prelates, chiefe rulers about church Government.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in this place with ♀ it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the natives to be dealers in pledges, Aromaticks, wine, or flowers.</p>
               <p>If in a nativity by night the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in this houſe with ♄, it ſignifies lazy ſlothfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in all their actions, attaining to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing which they deſire, ſpeaking ſacrile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious words againſt religion.</p>
               <p>If in a diurnall geniture the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in this houſe with ♂ and ☿, it ſignifies ſacrilegious perſons, unjuſt, irreligious, wicked Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 4th. houſe in a nativity by day ſignifies an ignoble Mother, and her husband to out-live her: but if ♄ be in any
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170163:79"/>other Angle of the geniture and ♀ in the weſt angle, it brings ſervitude or impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment to the mother.</p>
               <p>But if by night the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in this place at full, it ſignifies a Mother rich and noble, and greatly raiſes the natives by daily in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of riches.</p>
               <p>But if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in the 4th. houſe and the ☉ in the aſcendant, the natives receive de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerts of happineſſe, ſome by religion, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers by negotiations about women; but by day they ſignifie ignoble, wandring per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; their whoſe lives full of troubles and dangers; imployed ſomtimes in ſome ſervile office about the Church, eſpecially if any evill ſtarres behold the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 5th. houſe by night ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the native to have many Sonnes and joy with them or from them, but in a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urnall geniture ſhe giveth many daughters.</p>
               <p>In the 6th. houſe, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſing in light and well aſpected by good Planets, gives profit to the native by four footed beaſts, and health and ſoundneſſe of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy; but if beheld by the rayes of evill la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets, ſhe ſignifies miſerable humble ſervile laborious perſons.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 7th houſe, in a nocturnall geniture in thoſe ſignes wherein ſhe is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170163:79"/>or rejoyceth and increaſing in light, well Aſpected by ♃ or ♀ gives a happy old age, profit by women and a happy marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age, but if ſhe be oppreſſed by the male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volent beames of evill Planets, eſpecially in a diurnal geniture and decreaſe in light; ſhe hinders marriage, and when ſhe doth give a wife, ſhe is a widdow, barren or very much deformed and ilfavoured.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 8th. houſe, gives an eſtate by the dead, and denotes ſudden death to the native without paine or torment; but if ☍ or ♄ do behold her by <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, ſhe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſignifies lunaticks.</p>
               <p>In the 9th. houſe, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> being placed in a diurnall geniture, ſignifies the native to remaine ſordidly in the Churches, and to pretend to reveale ſomthing to men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared unto them from God; but in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity by night ſhe ſignifies divine worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of God, religious perſons, having ſome office about the Church, men of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Cogitations, if ſhe be in the houſe of ☿, Aſtronomers; if of ♀, ſingers; if the houſe of ♂, Armourers, makers of weapons; if the houſe of ♃, devout perſons, well skill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the law; if of ♄, Chymiſts; if the houſe of the ☉ profit by fourfooted beaſts; if ſhe be in ♋, her own houſe, the native hath
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170163:80"/>knowledge in all things belonging to the water.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 10th. houſe, in a nocturnall geniture in a ſigne wherein ſhe is exalted or rejoyceth, and increaſe in light and be well Aſpected by ♃, ſignifies great potent perſons having in their hands the power of life and death, great Counſellors, Dukes, Magiſtrates, happy in all their actions.</p>
               <p>But if ♄ be in any other Angle of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture, it ſignifies much envy and unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to oppreſſe the native.</p>
               <p>In a nativity by day, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 10th. houſe ſignifies the native to be ſubject to be deceived in all his actions; but if the ☉ be in the firſt in his own houſe, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, or in the houſe of ♃ it ſignifies great potent perſons, happy in their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 11th. houſe, hath the ſame ſignification, as in the fifth houſe is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 12th. houſe, in a nocturnall geniture, ſignifies long life; but if ♃ or ♀, or either of them, be in the aſcendant, it ſignifies power and happineſſe.</p>
               <p>But if ♄ or ♂, in a nocturnall geniture, be in the aſcendant or one of them, and the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170163:80"/>
                  <hi>Moen</hi> in the 12th, it ſignifies many evills misfortunes, and ſickneſſe, both to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and his Mother.</p>
               <p>But if there be no Planet in the aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the 12th. houſe in a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity by day, it ſignifies miſery and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the eſtate,</p>
               <p>Or if ſhe be alone in this houſe by night, ſhe ſignifies miſerable ſervile laborious men; their bodies having a filthy ſavour, ſubject often to be deceived, and ſuffer loſs by ſtrange Journeys,</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſo placed in the place of fortune and apply to ♃, or be with him, fignifies great happineſſe and magiſtracy.</p>
               <p>If with ♀, or apply to ♀, denotes much honeſty; if ſhe apply to ☿, <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gnifies men hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, potent, ingenious, cordiall, by learning raiſing themſelves to dignity and increaſe of their eſtate.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in this place and apply to ♂, it ſignifies miſerable laborious perſons, laboring in fire or about Iron, and getting their living thereby; if ſhe apply to ♄, it ſignifies the native to ſpend both his Fathers, and Mothers eſtate, and to die an eriſt death.</p>
               <p>In all genitures the courſe of the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> is to be diligently obſerved, not only on the
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170163:81"/>very day of the birth, but alſo we ought di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently to inquire on the 3. day of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity to what ſtarre and by what Aſpect ſhe is joyned, from whom ſhe ſeparates and to whom ſhe applies, whether ſhe increaſe or decreaſe in light, and what malevolent ſtarres behold her; for the 3d. day gives the ſame Judgment in all things as the firſt: which being diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and collected together, we can never erre in giving judgment of the fates of men by their nativities.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> apply or be carryed to ♄, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in light, it ſignifies widdow-hood to the mother, deſtruction of the eſtate and much misfortune.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſe in light and apply to ♃, or be joyned to him, it ſignifies rich, faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, honeſt, happy perſons; if ♂ do not behold her by a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍; otherwiſe, it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies much miſery and unhappineſſe.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſing apply to ♂, or be joyned to him in a nocturnall geniture, it ſignifies crafty, violent, dangerous per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, often ſubject to be deceived: by day, weake feeble bodies; ſubject to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes about the eyes and ſtomach, and to dye a violent death.</p>
               <pb n="145" facs="tcp:170163:81"/>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be carryed to the ☉ or be joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to him, what part of the ſcheame ſoever it be in, it ſignifies miſerable perſons, in all things unfortunate; afflicted daily with ſickneſſe.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be carryed to ♀, and ♀ partilely receive the beames of the approaching <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, and if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſing apply her ſelfe to the ♂ of ♀, if ſignifies noble Parents, but the natives to be ſeperated from their affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and miſerably burdened with want; but they are well known, noble, full of grace and honeſty, and in proces of time gaine increaſe of eſtate.</p>
               <p>But if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſing, apply ſo to ♀, ſhe ſignifies power &amp; happineſſe in youth, but to be ſcandalized with daily reports, unchaſt luſtful and burning in luſt towards women, eſpecially if ♂ behold them with a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, and the evills are the greater if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> and ♀ be in the houſe of ♄ or <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g>, without the teſtimony of ♃.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be joyned to ☿, ſhe ſignifies e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquent orators; eſpecially if ☿ be wel plac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his own ſignes or tearmes, or ♃ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them with a ▵.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ♄, and apply to ♃, it denotes rich wealthy happy perſons.</p>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:170163:82"/>
               <p>The full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperating from ♄ and apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ♂, ſignifies much ſickneſſe and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, and the native to dye in his youth.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ♄, and apply to the ☉, it is very unfortunate, and ſignifies many calamities, madneſſe lunatick, Dropſies, and the like to happen to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive daily, during his life.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperating from ♄ and applying to ♀ ſignifies noble happy rich wealthy perſons, but libidinous, and thereby to ſuffer infamy: if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſe in light, it denotes the native, to cover unlawfull loves; impure and immodeſt luſts, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe ſeeking after and gaining an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate and riches.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ♄, and apply to ☿ and be increaſing, ſhe ſignifies, obſcure cloſe perſons, guilty of writing unlawfull letters, ſtudying celeſtiall ſciences, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall arts, good Orators and Phyſitians.</p>
               <p>But if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g>, decreaſe in light, ſhe impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dites the ſpeech, or hearing; the body is ſickly, ſubject to the ſpleene, melancholy, Coughs, Dropſies and daily griefes of the Cholick.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ♃ and apply to ♂ in a nocturnall geniture, and be increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, it denotes magiſtrates, men in great
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170163:82"/>power, but holding their power in grea care and danger, and not without ſickneſſe.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperating from ♃ and applying to the ☉, deſtroyes all the patrimony of Father and Mother, the native to live from his Parents; exiles, fugitives, ſlaves, Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives; eſpecially if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be in the houſe of ♄ or♂.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſing or at full ſeperate from ♃, and apply to ♀, it ſignifies noble potent powerfull perſons, but to live from their own houſe, ſoone to want their parents, but nevertheleſſe it ſignifies happineſſe in the latter part of their age; honeſt grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courteous perſons; and much hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to gaines by their wives.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ♃ and apply to ☿, he ſignifies Judges, Collectors of money interpreters of the law, religious perſons, in all things happy.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ♃ and apply to ♄ and be increaſing or at full, it ſignifies the native to be adopted by a ſtranger; tutors or teachers of Children; to be imployed in moiſt watry places; Saylers, Pilgrims: but if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be decreaſing, it ſignifies ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, misfortune, captivity, continual ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs &amp; miſery; a miſerable death; if it be a nocturnall geniture, a violent death.</p>
               <pb n="148" facs="tcp:170163:83"/>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ♂ and apply to the ☉, it ſignifies very great evills, misfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes, ſhortneſſe of life, infelicity, a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent death, and to dye in a ſtrange Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperating from ♂ and applying to ♀ at full or increaſing, denotes Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous libidinous lecherous perſons, loving and coveting libidinous Venereous acts, and thereby oftentimes involving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into dangers; it ſignifies Jewellers, painters, perfumers, commonly dealers in mettals; and ſomtimes according to the nature of the ſigne, Vintners, Innkeepers, Victuallers.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be decreaſing in light, it ſignifies fortunate happy perſons, ſollicitors about women and getting wealth by them; gaining by their wives eſtate and credit, but ſomtimes ſuffering diſgrace by Venere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous acts, alwayes addicted to promiſcuous luſts.</p>
               <p>The full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperating from ♂, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to ☿ in a nocturnall geniture, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies great perſons, in great publique authority, but wicked, malicious, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes coveting to do wickedneſſe: if it be in a nativity by day, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> at full, it ſignifies them to receive a publique ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170163:83"/>of condemnation from the mouth of a Judge; and therefore to be put to a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent death.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ♂ and apply to ♄-it denotes ſluggiſh dull perſons, profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for nothing; if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be at full or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, deſtroyers of their eſtate, full of ſundry vices.</p>
               <p>But if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be decreaſing, it denotes hunger, ſickneſſe, Lunaticks, falling ſickneſſe, Hemorhoids, and to dye a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent death.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ♂, and apply to ♃ it ſignifies powerfull rich fortunate per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: but if ſhe be decreaſing in light, it afflicts the native with ſecret hidden vices, and frequent ſickneſſe.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in a diurnall geniture ſeperating from the ☉ and applying to ♀ ſignifies bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennes, hinders marriage, and Children; denotes prepoſterous loves, filthy uncleane luſts; perſons addicted to ſervile ſtudies, and occupied in ſervile actions, ſubſiſting and maintayning themſelvs by their owne endevours, and in proceſſe of time living happily.</p>
               <p>But in a nativity by night it ſignifies the native to have many wives, to be grate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, acceptable, well beloved, living in cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170163:84"/>and getting a great eſtate.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperating from the ☉ and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to ☿ in a diurnall geniture, ſigm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the native to be full of danger in all his life and actions; of evill manners, ſacrilegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, denying the Divinity.</p>
               <p>In a nocturnall geniture, ſignifies pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Notaries, Scriveners, inventers of occult and ſecret writing, or unlawfull letters, finders out of ſecret things; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſome gaine an eſtate, if not hindred by ♄ or ♂.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperating from the ☉ in a diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall geniture, and applying to ♄, deſtroyes an eſtate, divides one from his parents and brings him to want and miſery, but in proceſſe of time gives an eſtate and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe, but by night it ſignifies want; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of ones eſtate, much ſickneſſe and affliction.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperating from the ☉ and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying to ♃ by day, ſignifies a great eſtate, good fortune, and happineſſe beyond meaſure: but in a nocturnall geniture the natives get their eſtate by their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, are ſubject to daily travails, apt to be deceived in their youth, but in age they live in good credit and gaine good e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates.</p>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:170163:84"/>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> apply from the ☉ to ♂ in a diur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall geniture, it ſignifies ſudden death to the parents and want to the native, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the parents dye a violent death, the natives are ſubject to blindneſſe or defects in the ſight, lame, feeble bodyes, they dye young, ſomtimes a violent death; if it be a nocturnall geniture, it ſignifies cruell violent perſons, their imployment to be about fire, Iron or Mettals; ſubject to continuall labour.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> parting from ♀ and applying to ☿ if ſhe be increaſing or at full, ſignifies ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of noble women, thereby gaining preferment; it denotes alſo Dyers, Jew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ellers, Armourers, delighters in Muſick, but libidinous; ſubject to daily luſts, but gratefull and amiable in venereous acts, but if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſe, it ſignifies vitious uncleane perſons, but of various imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments as Orators, makers of images, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracers, Painters, ſuſteyning the care of others pleaſures and delights.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> eperating from ♀ and applying to ♄, at full or increaſing in a nocturnall geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, gives a wife that is a publique com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon woman or ſome of his kindred.</p>
               <p>If it be a diurnall geniture and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, the native is addicted to filthy luſts
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170163:85"/>and vitious delights, and through libidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous acts getting great diſgrace and infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, ſervile wandring, filthy perſons, Bauds and keepers of Whore-houſes; if the native be a woman ſhe will be a common Whore.</p>
               <p>If it be in a nocturnall geniture, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes barren perſons, Eunuchs, He mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prodites; if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ♀ and apply to ♃, it ſignifies Noble men, Cheif Magiſtrates of Citties; grateful, Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, lovers of women; if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſe, it ſignifies the natives to gain much by wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maen, to live happy from their youth, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining to poſſeſſions, great gaines, or ſome honorable office in the Church.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperating from ♀ and applying to ♂, in a diurnall Geniture at full or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, ſignifies miſery, deſtruction, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſonment, or a ſudden death by reaſon of the love of ſome one.</p>
               <p>but if in nocturnall Geniture, the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſo apply to ♂, it ſignifies cruell perſons in great power, but ſubject to daily dangers and miſchances.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be transferred from ☿ to the ☉, it ſeperates the native from his parents by ſome bitter falling out. Whereby he is cruell burdened with want, full of trouble,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170163:85"/>but unchaſt and miſerably afflicted with love: but after youth is paſt, in proces of time, he increaſeth his eſtate, and eaſily attaines his deſires.</p>
               <p>If in a diurnall Geniture the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſeperate from ☿ and apply to ♄, it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes deaſneſſe, flammerers, or ſuch as have ſome impediment in their ſpeech, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters, priers into ſecret acts, laylors: but if it be a nativity by night, it ſignifies watermen, or men imployed to labour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the water: but if malevolent ſtarrs afflict them, it denotes impriſonment and ill fortune to the native.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be transferred from ☿ to ♃, it ſignifies great men, Embaſſadours, Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers ſtewards of Noble men, prieſts, rich, happy perſons.</p>
               <p>If the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be increaſing, or at full, or ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply from ☿ to ♂ in a diurnall Geniture; it ſignifies irreligious, perjured, fallacious, wicked perſons, full of malice, their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe daily increaſing, Theeves, Robbers, Church-Breakers, Homicides, murderers, and for ſome wicked act, to ſuffer a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent death.</p>
               <p>If it be in a Nocturnall Geniture and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> at full or increaſing appyly to ♂, it ſignifies Captaines Governors, of cities,
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170163:86"/>men in great power, but terrible tyrants, never ſtanding long in their power, but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers wayes offending, and therefore to be depoſed baniſhed or put to a violent death: if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeperate from ☿, and apply to the Sun, it ſignifies men dull in their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, impedited in their ſpeech, deaf, poor wandring people, having no Conſtant dwelling houſe: but in proceſs of time, theſe evils will be qualified, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the time of youth is paſt they gain a lively hood by ſundry imployments; if in a Nocturnall Geniture the full <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> ſeparate from ☿ and ayply to ♀, it ſignifies men imployed in publique actions, getting Credit and honour in all their actions, and increaſe of hapineſſe; it ſignifies ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, men of fluent tongues, poets; gaining by women and womens affaires; Makers of painting Pictures and Colours, Mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cines, Iewellers, but living meanly neither abounding nor in want, intemperate in venereous acts, and thereby getting ſome diſgrace.</p>
               <p>But if in a nocturnall geniture the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be decreaſing and apply to ♀, it ſignifies rich and wealthy perſons, having the cheife government of ſome Townes or Cities; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be free from the beames
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:170163:86"/>of the ☉ and ſo likewiſe ♀. But if this ♂ be in the other places of the geniture, it ſignifies men alwaies of honeſt actions and gaining an eſtate by their own: if in a nativity by day the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> decreaſing by joyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ♀, and this ♂ be in the 10th. houſe, it ſignifies religious perſons, builders of Churches, Prelates or men bearing great Offices in the Church; but in any other places of the geniture, this ♂ ſignifies men of meane eſtates; occupied in arts about mettals; or Leather-dreſſers, ſellers of perfumes or ſweete ſpices; poliſhers of precious Jewells, Colourers of Gemms and Jewells, ingravers of Images; buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Choriſters, ſuch as have knowledge in celeſtiall ſciences; learned in hidden and ſecret arts: and by ſuch meanes, gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their lively-hood.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="chapter">
               <pb n="156" facs="tcp:170163:87"/>
               <head>The Signification of the <hi>12</hi> Signes or Houſes in the four Angles of Heaven. <hi>CHAP. XXXII.</hi> The Signification of the Horoſcope in <hi>Aries.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF the Horoſcope be found in ♈ the <hi>Medium Caeli</hi> in ♑ the 7th. houſe in <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra,</hi> and the fourth in ♋; we come now generally to explaine what the Horo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcope in ♈, and the other three Angels ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies.</p>
               <p>The Horoſcope in ♈ for the moſt part ſignifies youth, denyeth any brethren, or only one liveth of many, and he is debili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by the bitterneſſe of ſome vice, whereby his name is hated: he keepeth not his Fathers eſtate in the ſame ſtate, it was left him; but ſomtimes waſtes and ſpends it, and againe gathers it together: to ſome he will ſeeme free from too much
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170163:87"/>liberality, and diſpleaſe others with his free liberality; beſtowing benefits upon un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratefull perſons that will never give him thanks; he will be mutable unconſtant, and ſubject to griefes and paines in the head.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Medium Caeli</hi> be alſo partilely in ♑, he will perſevere to attaine to ſome ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable acts, and flatter with a certaine humility, he will be placed in ſome office, chiefe in ſome learned imployment, maintayning many, procureing eſtates to others; ingenious in many neceſſary things; penetrating into celeſtiall ſecrets if ☿ behold that place or be in that houſe.</p>
               <p>The third Angle the 7th. houſe chaleng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, wherein if ♎ be poſited, it ſignifies the native to be a daily ſervant in the houſes of Kings or Princes, or imployed in publique actions, but their lives to be mutable, and of an unequall fortune, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>felicity following happineſſe, and mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune proſperity, caſting them ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly down from the higheſt degree of digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the loweſt of humility, envy alwaies fighting againſt their happineſſe; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if ♃ do not behold the Horoſcope by a ▵ or be not poſited therein, the evils are the ſtronger.</p>
               <pb n="158" facs="tcp:170163:88"/>
               <p>The next Angle is the 4th. houſe. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in if ♋ be found, and the Horoſcope in ♈, it ſignifies famous happy perſons; if ♃ be in the aſcendant, and behold that place, or be in that place; but ſome of the natives kindred will be adverſaries to him, either becauſe of himſelfe, or of ſome neceſſary thing belonging to him, he will be ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did and ſlovenly in his haire; but will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes have plenty of all neceſſaries, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially if ♃ be found in any Angle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIII. <hi>Of the Horoſcope in</hi> Taurus.</head>
               <p>THe Horoſcope in <hi>Taurus</hi> alwayes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notes the native to be defatigated with many labours, loſing whatſoever he gets in his youth; but afterwards whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he loſt before, he ſhall cheerefully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and a plentifull increaſe of happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe he ſhall ſee his enemyes miſerably caſt down and kept in continuall ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; if the <hi>Medium Caeli</hi> be in ♒, he ſhall alwayes be in favour and freindſhip a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170163:88"/>great men, and his whole life ſhall be converſant in publique actions, and his imployment for the moſt part to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the water; ſometimes enviouſly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, but he ſhall have increaſe of riches as well as loſſe.</p>
               <p>If the 7th. houſe be the ſigne, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive will be prudent in the whole conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of his life, nouriſhing others by ſome Office of his procuring, burying his firſt wife; and if the native be a woman, ſhe buryeth her husband and a ſonne.</p>
               <p>If the 4th. houſe be in <hi>Leo,</hi> the native gaines an eſtate by his own proper labour and by divers kindes of wyles gaines a great eſtate, but alwayes living happily, but theſe things are to be judged according to the nature of the geniture.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="chapter">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:170163:89"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXIIII. <hi>Of the Horoſcope in</hi> Gemini.</head>
               <p>IF the Horoſcope be found in ♊ it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies the native to begin his life with la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; to receive comfort from his parents, bound in freind-ſhip to wicked men; Which gives his patrimony.</p>
               <p>If the <hi>Medium Caeli</hi> be in ♓, it ſignifies the native to live in watry places, and to poſſeſſe his eſtate and patrimony, to gaine his livelihood by other mens endevours, and either to be potent in two Citties, or to divide his patrimony.</p>
               <p>If the Weſt Angle be in ♐, he brings ſome damage to himſelfe or his kindred occaſioned by him, and his minde to be troubled with many cares by reaſon of the various changes of the time, he ſhall have many enemies, and be beaten out of his own Country to wander in ſtrange Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; but afterwards ſhall returne to his own Country, and his eſtate be reſtored unto him.</p>
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:170163:89"/>
               <p>The 4th, houſe in ♍ ſignifies the firſt part of the natives age; ſhall be wearyed with the continuation of many labours, but in proceſs of time to attaine to many felicities and much happineſſe; but all theſe things are to be conſidered by the poſition or the whole geniture, which we have frequently deſired you, diligently to obſerve.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXV. <hi>The Horoſcope in</hi> Cancer.</head>
               <p>THe Horoſcope in <hi>Cancer</hi> ſignifies acute ingenious perſons, doing al things with moderation; ſubject to much anger; but the ſame is ſoone mitigated and quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; they ſubſiſt by publique imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments or offices, uſing much flattery.</p>
               <p>If the Horoſcope be in ♋ and ♄ therein, it ſignifies a violent death, or much ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, or their own brothers to ſuffer for their vices.</p>
               <p>If ♈ be in the 10th. houſe or <hi>Medium Caeli,</hi> it ſignifies the native to lead his life
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170163:90"/>amongſt great men, to have his daily ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance from other mens eſtates, alwaies ſeeking after and deſiring good things; but his eſtate ſubject to mutability, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times looſing and as often gaining.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Capricorne</hi> in the 7th. houſe denotes the native ſhall be troubled with ſome daily hidden afflictions, but the ſame ſhall be appeaſed after, much diſprofit; he will be ingenious in his actions and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, but ſuſteyning ſome ſecret griefe, and his minde afflicted with many for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Libra,</hi> in the 4th. bouſe or <hi>Imum Caeli,</hi> denotes the native ſhall ſuffer many la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; applying to civill women, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in popular imployments, he will waſt the ſubſtance of his patrimony that is left him; he will be in power, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to others; well learned and truſted with others ſecrets; attaining to a very old age, and have an honorable buriall.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Mercury</hi> be in the following ſigne, he will be preferred before all his brethren; but if ♀ be in the 2d. houſe, the daughters have moſt preferment, if the Lord of the geniture be well placed, and Aſpected by benevolent ſtarres.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="chapter">
               <pb n="163" facs="tcp:170163:90"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXVI. <hi>Of the</hi> Horoſcope <hi>in</hi> Leo</head>
               <p>IF the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> be found in ♌ he that hath this aſcendant ſhall be ſubject to much labour and many dangers, well known, alwayes ingenious, one having free power; not expreſſing his malice in all things, deſirous to live and Rule; and get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Subſtance of his eſtate by his own endeavours; but if ♂ be partilely placed in the aſcendant, or the ☉ behold him with a <g ref="char:quadrine">□</g> or ☍, he denies having any Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, but if ♃ be found ſo placed, he gives one daughter.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Medium Caeli</hi> in ♉ ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to live in ſome publique imployment or in the Church, to Contract marriage with ſome widdow, whore, ſervile perſon, or old woman or one publiquely infamous he ſhall receive his greateſt honour from ſome potent perſon; he will be Ignorant, but nevertheleſſe ſhall have a proſperous increaſe of fortune.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fortune alwayes favours fools.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:170163:91"/>
               <p>If ♒ be in the 7th. houſe, it ſignifies his life ſhall be ſubject both to loſſe and gain, he will be gratefull and approved in ſome things.</p>
               <p>If ♏ be in the 4th. houſe, he will be the Chief in ſome imployments, but if ☍ do behold this place by any aſpect, he will ſometimes be impriſoned; if ♂ be ſo poſited and orientall, he will be a ſouldier or Commander of an army; but will dye in ſome ſtrange and forraigne place, a Sud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den or violent death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXVII. <hi>The</hi> Horoſcope <hi>in</hi> Virgo.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Horoſcope</hi> being in ♍, ſignifies many Cares and troubles to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, he will be skilfull in telling things to come, much ſubject to unlawfull lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, Coveting the Society of many women; but he ſhall labour with theſe vices but untill the <hi>Anaphora</hi> of his ſigne be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated. He will he well learned humane, friendly, knowing much and ſeeking into all ſecret learning, of a good memory:
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:170163:91"/>gaining ſome office by his learning, and thereby great increaſe of his eſtate.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Medium Caeli</hi> in ♊, ſignifies an eſtate by publique or religious imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; in his old age, a devote worſhipper of God, and having ſome government of a City, ſeeking after hidden things but Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of much learning; juſt and upright in the latter part of his age.</p>
               <p>If ⚹ be in the 7th. houſe the native ſhall travaile in many ſtrange places, and he known to many men, many will flatter him; he will be gratefull, happy, amiable, acute, full of much Imployment, in all his Converſation Noble.</p>
               <p>The 4th. houſe in ♐ ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive will be happy, receiving an eſtate from his friends, many will flatter him, he will rejoyce in the happineſſe of his Children, but ſhall grieve for the loſſe of ſome of them; he will be apt and fit for all things, learned and happy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="chapter">
               <pb n="166" facs="tcp:170163:92"/>
               <head>CHAP. XXXVIII. <hi>The Signification of the</hi> Horoſcope <hi>in</hi> Libra.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LIbra</hi> in the aſcendant, ſignifies much ſickneſſe many troubles and dangers, many adverſaries; the native will be religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, a worſhipper of God; but his life much ſubject to mutability, but incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable in all things; the later part of his time will be more glorious, but hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing few Children, of a right &amp; ſincere Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in all things, proceeding from a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and heavenly minde.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cancer</hi> in the 10th. ſignifies he will be oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pucied in ſome famous actions, his old age will be honorable pentifull, rich and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, having a good eſtate, but few Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. But if ♃, behold this place by any aſpect, he will have a happy off-ſpring.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aries</hi> in the 7th. houſe, ſignifies pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit to the Native by the water or watry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; he will be fearefull, he will be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of his life in ſome deſert place, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170163:92"/>to dangers and ſudden travailes, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome hidden vice; and happineſſe in his old age.</p>
               <p>The 4th. houſe in ♑, the natives eſtate ſhall be ſubject to mutability; ſomtimes loſing and againe getting what he loſt, but he ſhall get all his eſtate by his own proper induſtry, and the latter part of his eſtate ſhall be very happy.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XXXIX. <hi>The Horoſcope in</hi> Scorpio.</head>
               <p>THe Horoſcope in ♏ ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to be acute in youth, angry, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to many misfortunes, but afterwards happy, and given much to mirth; if ♃ be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold him by any Aſpect, they will be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, religious, and magnified by their own Studies, alwaies high ſpirited, run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning into ſome danger by reaſon of their friends or buſineſs, and after many infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes by the loſs of Children, they ſhall reioyce in an happy Off-ſpring.</p>
               <pb n="168" facs="tcp:170163:93"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> in the Mid-heaven, ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſhall be wearied with many labours, and obliged to ſome great perſon for ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or maintenance; he will be valiant, and in proceſs of time flattered by many; and by this means will raiſe many others: he will be placed in ſome authority, and increaſe his eſtate left him by his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taurus</hi> in the weſt Angle, ſignifies the native ſhall be oppreſt with many adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, alwaies covetous of venerous acts, and ſubject to ſome infamy or diſgrace; he ſhall get an eſtate, and loſe it again, and afterwards regain it again.</p>
               <p>♒ In the fourth Houſe, ſignifies danger of life by water, and to whomſoever the native ſhall be profitable, they will always be ingrateful to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="chapter">
               <pb n="169" facs="tcp:170163:93"/>
               <head>CHAP. XL. <hi>The Horoſcope in</hi> Sagittary.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>SAgittary</hi> in the Aſcendant, ſignifies the native ſhall have many adverſaries; but an eſtate conferred upon him which he hoped not for: he will be frequently in ſtrange Countries, going much by Sea, in publick employments, converſant on the water, or about watery places, having much Learning, Prudent, Ingenious, and skilful in all Arts.</p>
               <p>♍ In the tenth, denotes he ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to great power, the common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhall obey him, and many ſhall ſubſiſt by him; but on whomſoever he beſtows any thing, they will alwaies be unthankful un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him.</p>
               <p>♊ in the ſeventh, ſignifies the native ſhall have children and nephews in his
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170163:94"/>old age; he ſhall eaſily overcome all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and loſſes, addicted to ſecret lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, ingenuous, juſt and prudent, alwaies overtaking his adverſary with ſubtil diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations, teaching all things, and in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of time, attaining to happineſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piſces</hi> in the fourth or <hi>Imum Caeli,</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates the native ſhall gain his livelihood about the water, or in watery places; hee will be of good credit, known, and noble, diſaffected to a wife or marriage, unleſs ♃ behold that place by ſome Aſpect, then he eaſily takes a wife, and is well affected to her; but ſhe is a whoriſh or adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous woman.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="chapter">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:170163:94"/>
               <head>CHAP. XLI. <hi>Of the Horoſcope in</hi> Capricorn.</head>
               <p>THe Horoſcope in ♑, ſignifies the native will be faithfull in his freind-ſhip to his friends, ſubtill, and wanting nothing that appertaines to the ſuſtenance of his life, he will travaile in ſtrange Countryes and relieve ſtrangers, but they will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be ingratefull to him; he will be amiable, of a little Spirit, a long life, and wealthy; abounding in luſt to women; and contemning &amp; diſpraiſing them when his luſt is ſatisfied; ſtudious to learne hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den ſecrets, either of others lives, or of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and holy things.</p>
               <p>The Mid-Heaven in ♎ denotes the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to be juſt, honeſt, learned, well-ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, performing vowes to God for delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from ſome danger or neceſſity: he will have good ſucceſſe in his actions, but afterwards ſome misfortune; yet he will gaine by the misfortune of others, and
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170163:95"/>have profit by others deaths, and gaines ſome ſecret profit by ſome antient thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cancer</hi> in the 7th. ſignifies the native to undergoe much trouble by his freinds or kindred, and to be ſubject to many dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aries</hi> in the 4th. houſe ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive will fall into many errors, and many disprofits; his life ſubject to change and mutability, ſomtimes in a high degree of dignity, and ſomtimes caſt downe in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity; he will have a wife and his firſt ſonne or what ſonne ſoever he hath, ſhall be much debilitated with ſickneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="chapter">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:170163:95"/>
               <head>CHAP. XLII. <hi>Of the Horoſcope in</hi> Aquarius.</head>
               <p>A Quary in the aſcendant ſignifies the native ſhall waſt and loſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he hath gotten, but ſhall againe gather it together; he will cheriſh and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve many, but in what ſtate ſoever he is placed he will be in many dangers, deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired, of by men, but delivered by the aſiſtance of God; he will be ſmitten by many with the ſtroke of envy, but he will be in ſome religious office, and well known by his good acts to great men.</p>
               <p>The Mid-Heaven in ♍ denotes the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive will be valiant, but leading a hard life and converſation, removing from place to place, if he be ingenious he will have ſome ſervile office; but the event of all his actions will be proſperous, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the beginning of his marriage he will ſuffer many misfortunes by his wife or Children, and afterwards much good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune is conferred upon him.</p>
               <pb n="174" facs="tcp:170163:96"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leo</hi> in the 7th. houſe ſignifieth the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive and his wife will live at variance; ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he will joyne himſelfe to ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy woman; or burne in love to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; and many enemies will riſe againſt him with ſome ſudden actions, and by his own power he will take a wife belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to another man or eſpouſed to another or a widdow.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taurus</hi> in the 4th. houſe ſignifies the native to be great and much converſant amongſt potent perſons; to gaine honour in all his actions, and much eſteemed for his learning, and to live a very old age; if the Lord of the geniture be alſo well poſited.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="chapter">
               <pb n="175" facs="tcp:170163:96"/>
               <head>CHAP. XLIII. <hi>Of the Horoſcope in</hi> Piſces.</head>
               <p>THe Horoſcope in ♓, ſignifies ingenious prudent perſons, faithfull friends; but having many enemies, and eaſily vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating himſelfe from them; inclined to tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, and negotiations in forraigne Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryes, and in proceſſe of time increaſe of eſtate and felicity.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Medium-Caeli</hi> in ♑ involvs the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive into many troubles and dangers; hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many great variances with potent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſubject to inſnare himſelfe for ſome other man; loſing all his firſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion and eſtate; and againe getting the dominion and poſſeſſion of another mans eſtate, by the meanes of ſome faithfull friend.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virgo</hi> in the 7th. houſe denotes the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to be prudent faithfull and helpfull to others, having many faithfull ſecrets com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to him; raiſing many friends by his helps, but they alwayes prove ingrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, he will attaine to much riches, and
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170163:97"/>greatneſſe, and have a loving tender af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection towards his wife, but ſhe will ſometimes be ingratefull to him, and he will ſuffer much misfortune by his Wife and Children.</p>
               <p>The fourth houſe in ♋ denotes much ſikneſſe and labour to the native, ſecret hidden greifes, but afterwards good for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune; on a ſudden an eſtate ſhall be confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon him to ſupply all his wants, and in his old age he ſhall dye ſuddenly in a ſtrange Country; but herein the Lord of the geniture is to be obſerved; for ſome will give another Judgment hereof, but this is the ſubſtantiall truth of it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="chapter">
               <pb n="177" facs="tcp:170163:97"/>
               <head>CHAP. XLIIII.</head>
               <p>THe aſcendant in the tearmes of <hi>Saturn</hi> doth ſignifie ſlow dull ſluggiſh perſons ſlow of ſpeech; alienated from all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, hated in all their actions, keeping anger long.</p>
               <p>If ♄ be in the aſcendant in his tearmes, he denyes the native to have any brothers or ſiſters, or the firſt borne to dye an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill death, or ſome evill fortune to befall them, and the native to have no Children.</p>
               <p>If ♃ be in the Horoſcope in the tearms of ♄, it ſignifies ſordid covetuous perſons, alwaies doing ſervile acts, and letting all their eſtate be at the diſpoſing of others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> ſo poſited ſignifies malicious, wicked, cruell perſons giving themſelves over totally to worke wickedneſſe; but their miſcheife is often diſcovered and brought to light.</p>
               <p>The ☉ ſo placed denotes men of tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite manners, but alwaies armed with envy, imperfect, and defective in their Counſells.</p>
               <pb n="178" facs="tcp:170163:98"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> thus placed ſignifies men ſordid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly laſcivious about Venereous acts, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes covetuous of other mens goods.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> in this place, ſignifies men ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>didly wicked in all their actions, often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times impriſoned, ſuffering much trouble by reaſon of their wickedneſſe.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> thus poſited and at full or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing, ſignifies men vaine, both in minde and body: but if the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> be decreaſing in light, ſhe vitiateth their bodyes with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignant humours; either dropſies, or a deformed pale Colour, or madneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="chapter">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:170163:98"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLV.</hi> Of the Horoſcope in the tearmes of <hi>Jupiter.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Horoſcope in the tearmes of ♃ ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies wife, vertuous perſons; and if ♃ be poſited there, magnanimous, but full of cruelty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> or ♂ in thoſe places by night ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies perfidious perſons, never keeping their credit or promiſe; wiſe in their own conceits, leading a poore life, full of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and miſery; but in a diurnall geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, theſe evills are in ſome ſort miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> thus placed ſignifies men apt to performe all good offices; but never hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing proſperous ſucceſſe in marriage; they are loving and daily reaping the fruits of felicity.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> poſited here, denotes perſons of good manners, free from malice; ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply and plainly underſtanding and diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many things.</p>
               <pb n="180" facs="tcp:170163:99"/>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> thus placed is very fortunate and gives ſoundneſſe and health of body.</p>
               <p>The ☉ in this place, ſignifies the ſame as the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> doth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XLVI. <hi>Of the</hi> Horoſcope <hi>in the tearms of</hi> Mars</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Horoſcope</hi> in the <hi>tearmes</hi> of ♂ alwayes ſignifies men of an acute quick Spirit; ♄ in this place ſignifies alſo acute Spirits, but long keepers of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the ſame place alſo ſignifies an acute ſharp wit, but ſuch as are deſirous alwayes to do good to others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> in the <hi>Horoſcope</hi> in his own tearmes, ſignifies in a diurnall Geniture men addicted to all wickedneſſe, but time<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and ſubject to unfortunare Changes; in a nocturnall Geniture, Cruel irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſons, deſtroyers of other mens goods.</p>
               <p>The full ☉ thus placed denotes crafty
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170163:99"/>ſubtill perſons, but oftentimes inſnared in treachery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> in this place ſignifies luſtfull adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> in this place ſignifies homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides, ſuch are given to wicked laſcivious and unlawfull luſts, and drunkenneſſe; ingenious, but ſeldom having any true Judgment of any thing.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> thus poſited, denotes men divers wayes contending with their adverſaries; and their adverſaries doing the like by them, they are very laborious, receiving ſome wound by fire or iron: but if it be a diurnall geniture, and the <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> at full, it gives a ſtrong body; if a nocturnall geniture, it denotes a ſtrong well compoſed body fit for labour; but covetuous, and alwayes dying a violent death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="chapter">
               <pb n="161" facs="tcp:170163:100"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVII.</hi> The Horoſcope in the tearmes of <hi>Venus.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Horoſcope in the tearmes of Venus ſignifies lovers of muſick, benevolent perſons, deſirous to be profitable to all men, in a diurnall geniture great digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty profit and good fortune,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn,</hi> thus placed in the tearmes of <hi>Venus,</hi> ſignifies ſcorners of women, haters of marriage, if it be a diurnall geniture; but in a nativity by night it ſignifies ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did uncleane immodeſt perſons, addicted to unnaturall luſts; not loving naturall coition; mutable in their Counſells, and haters of all goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter</hi> in this place ſignifies, tender de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licate but libidinous perſons, luxurious but free from envy and cruelty, mercifull in any office, their imployment to be apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning to the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars,</hi> in theſe termes in a diurnal ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niture gives ſudden troubles, loſſes many
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:170163:100"/>and ſeditions among the people, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he comes into much danger; but ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies lovers of muſick and poetry, engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, or the like.</p>
               <p>In a nocturnal geniture, ♂ in the tearmes of ♀, gives a double marriage, and great riches thereby; but withall much care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe.</p>
               <p>The ☉ thus placed, ſignifies the native to Proſper daily in his actions, but diſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in marriage and diſprofit thereby, but it gives gaines and love amongſt great men, alwayes favoured and commended by them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mercury</hi> in the tearmes of ♀, thus po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited in the aſcendant, ſignifies libidinous, wiſe, and of good manners; deſiring to profit others, Grammarians, Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Poets, Orators.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> thus placed, ſignifies Artificers, delighting in neat honeſt artes; Ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers; getting commendations by their worke; but in a nocturnall geniture, ſhe ſignifies fiſhermen, or ſuch as get their lively-hoods by ſuch imployments; ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies zealous perſons; of a good minde and underſtanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="chapter">
               <pb n="182" facs="tcp:170163:101"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XLVIII.</hi> Of the Horoſcope in the tearmes of <hi>Mercury.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe Horoſcope in the tearmes of ☿ ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies learned men, credited with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ffices of truſt, Orators, ſtewards of great men.</p>
               <p>If ☿ be therein placed, he ſignifies Aſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logers, Mathematians; doing vertuous offices, and eſteemed for their knowledge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saturn</hi> in the tearmes of ☿ ſignifies un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy cruell perſons, ſlow in their words and actions, great laborers, full of poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonous malice, long keepers of anger, of an evill report; interpreters of dreames, raſh in their Counſels.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jupiter</hi> in this place ſignifies men skilled in the law, phyſitians, advocates for great perſons, but luſtfull and adulterers; but in a nativity by night he ſignifies the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to be ſcriveners and of a good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port and credit unto the end of their lives.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mars</hi> thus placed in a diurnall geniture ſignifies wicked malicious perſons, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentious,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:170163:101"/>cruell, raſh, not ruled by reaſon, clamorous, impudent, full of raging pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſterous fury, hangmen, full of all wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſſe; but in a nativity by night, theſe evills are ſomthing qualified.</p>
               <p>The ☉ thus placed ſignifies famous No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men of popular applauſe and fame, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceders or advocates in the defence of the people, whereby they are publiquely known, exerciſing many offices; and if ☿ be thus poſited with the ☉, they do all things with ſound Counſel and reaſon, and are of an uncorrupt iudgment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Venus</hi> in the tearmes of ☿, hath the ſame ſignification as we have declared ☿ to have in the tearmes of ♀; ſhe ſignifies great hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py perſons, eaſily attaining their deſires in all things, learned merry perſons, lovers of muſick, Poets, famous for their verſes; gaining eſtates by others miſchances.</p>
               <p>The <g ref="char:Moon">☽</g> in the tearmes of ☿ in a diurnall geniture, maketh artificers, ſuch as are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred for their artificiall works; but in a nocturnal geniture, ſhe denotes ſuch as have knowledge in all arts, all manner of artiſts, delighting in all manner of exerciſes
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170163:102"/>ingenious, dealing in Merchants and for reign affaires, knowing all things, and for divers cauſes are transferred from one place to another, and ſtriving to hide and diſſemble all grief and infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:170163:102"/>
            <head>Books ſold by <hi>John Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> at the Riſing Sun in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard between the two North doores in the New Building, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Divinity.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>BEzain Novum Teſtamentum, in folio</item>
                  <item>Doctor <hi>Holdſworth</hi> works com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plear, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Carylls</hi> fifth Vol. <hi>Job</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>— his ſeventh Vol. on <hi>Job</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Grenhills</hi> ſecond Vol. on <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Cradocks</hi> Goſpel-liberty, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>Mr. <hi>Lockyers</hi> works in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>Biſhop <hi>Andrews</hi> Catechiſticall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Simſons</hi> Juſtification, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>Doctor <hi>Ainſworth,</hi> Communion of Saints, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>— His Arrow againſt Idolatry, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>Welſh Teſtament, 12<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:170163:103"/>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richardſons</hi> Saints deſire, 120.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Jacob Behme</hi> of Election and predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>H. N. His firſt exhortation to the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of Love, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cotton</hi> on the Covenant, 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Books of Art.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Streets</hi> Ephemerides, with <hi>Keplers</hi> way of direction for Nativities.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Magia Adamica;</hi> or, the anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of Magicks. by <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo lothes</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Lumen de Lumine;</hi> or, a new magicall Light. by <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo lothes</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Anthropoſopia Theomagica.</hi> by <hi>Euge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo lothes</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Caeleſtis Legatus; or the Celeſtiall</hi> Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador, by <hi>John Gadbury, &amp;c:</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Opus Aſtrologicum, ſold by</hi> Richard Moon <hi>at the ſeven Starrs, in</hi> Pauls Church-yard.</item>
               </list>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
